<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The art of stenographie teaching by plaine and certaine rules, to the capacitie of the meanest, and for the vse of all professions, the way of compendious writing. Wherevnto is annexed a very easie direction for stegan'ographie, or, secret writing.</title>
            <author>Willis, John, d. 1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15478</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840560</idno>
  <idno type="VID">5076</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248565748</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 25744A</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S104829</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99840560e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15478)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5076)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 863:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The art of stenographie teaching by plaine and certaine rules, to the capacitie of the meanest, and for the vse of all professions, the way of compendious writing. Wherevnto is annexed a very easie direction for stegan'ographie, or, secret writing.</title>
                  <author>Willis, John, d. 1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[100] p. : table  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by W. White] for Cuthbert Burbie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Willis.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes folded table, bound after G2, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F G² .</note>
                  <note>some pages marked.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Shorthand --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5076:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5076:1"/>
            <p>THE ART OF STENOGRAPHIE, Teaching by plaine and certaine Rules, to the capacitie of the <hi>meanest, and for the vse of</hi> all professions, <hi>The way of compendious Writing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherevnto is annexed a very easie direction for <hi>Steganógraphie,</hi> or, Secret Writing.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Horat. serm. lib. 1. Satyr. 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Si quid promittere de me</l>
               <l>Possum aliud, verè promitto.</l>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device?: eagle feeding its young</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed for <hi>Cuthbert Burbie.</hi> 1602.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:5076:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5076:2"/>
            <head>The Proeme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the profite and easinesse of the Art of <hi>Stenographie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore the preceptes of this Art be deliuered, it shall not be amisse for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter encouragement of the Reader thervnto, to note briefly, how profitable it is for vse, and how easie to be atteyned.</p>
            <p>Concerning the profit, there are fiue se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall respectes wherein it ministreth espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall helpe and furtherance.</p>
            <p>First, in short or compendious writing: by conteyning that in one line, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing written with letters at large, would take vp foure lines or more: in which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect it hath a profitable vse, for the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of briefe Notes of remembrance, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlineations,
<pb facs="tcp:5076:3"/> marginall Notes, and such like.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in speedie writing: For he that is well practized in this Art, may write <hi>Verbatim,</hi> as fast as a man can treateably speake: In regard whereof, it is very neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie, for the noting of Sermons, Orations, Mootes, Reportes, Disputations, and the like.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in secret writing: For euen the very Characters and order, of their places taught by this Booke, doe deliuer such a forme of writing, as is secret enough to all that are not acquainted with this Art: But if any be desirous to set a further locke on his Notes and Writinges, he may out of those few and easie directions taught in the ende of this Booke for that purpose, be fully satisfied in the same.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, this Booke discouereth a true and constant forme of Art, applyable not to one Language alone, but generally to all; in so much that he which hath lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it throughly, as it concernerh the English onely, may by the same skill, write also in Latine, French, Italian, or any other Tongue that he hath knowledge of: And
<pb facs="tcp:5076:3"/> therefore this Booke may serue for a good ground and president to him that shall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to set foorth the <hi>Stenographie</hi> of any other Language.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, the ingenious Reader may here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by strengthen his memorie in the sure ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehension of any speech or sentence, which he would lay vp in that Treasurie.</p>
            <p>And touching the easinesse of this Art, as the preceptes are all apparantly short; so the Characters deuised for the expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of all wordes, are few in number: to wit, but 28. in all.</p>
            <p>The Rules also are certaine, and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in consequence of reason the one vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the other: squared and fitted to the three lawes of Art, each principle being deliuered but once generally, and in his proper place.</p>
            <p>Also, by Notes vpon euery Chapter are explaned such wordes and Characters vsed in the Rules or Examples, as might seeme to meaner capacities hard or doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>And the whole frame of this worke is so contriued, that the memorie shall not neede to be charged with a tedious labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:5076:4"/> of a multitude of Wordes and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters by hart; but enured onely to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise order.</p>
            <p>Lastly, these thinges are herein perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in so plaine and direct a manner, as will enable any of indifferent iudgement, vpon once reading ouer these few Rules with good aduise, to vndertake foorthwith the forme of Writing by them prescribed, wherein he shall quickly attaine great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinesse, if he but practise it in his ordinarie businesse, as occasion serueth, and thereby keepe it without all danger of loosing it: But if through many yeeres discontinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, the methode hereof should be cleane forgotten, yet two or three howers labour bestowed in perusing once more this short Booke, will sufficiently awaken his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, and put his hand againe in true motion to write according to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes of this Art.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:5076:4"/>
            <head>THE ART OF STENOGRAPHIE. The first Booke.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 1. Of great Characters.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Tenographie <hi>(a)</hi> is the Art of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Writing.</p>
               <p>It consisteth of two parts: the abre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiation of a word, and the abreuiation of a sentence. <hi>(b)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A worde is abreuiated, when it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed by a short Character, <hi>(c)</hi> agreable vnto it.</p>
               <p>A Character is a lineall <hi>(d)</hi> note of any thing, <hi>(e)</hi> as, the Characters a b c d e f, are lineall <hi>(f)</hi> notes <hi>(g)</hi> of letters, 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. of number, ♄ ♃ ♂ of Planets.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:5"/>
               <p>Vnto Characters belong Figure and Quantitie.</p>
               <p>The figure of a Character, is the forme whereby it is distinguished from all other: as, the Figure of foure is 4. the Figure of <hi>Saturne</hi> is ♄.</p>
               <p>The quantitie of a Character is mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured by two straight Lines parallel <hi>(h)</hi> thwart <hi>(i)</hi> expressed or vnderstood. <hi>(k)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Character is of quantitie, great, or small.</p>
               <p>A great Character is Interlineall, or Transcendent. <hi>(l)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Interlineall occupieth so much space as is the distance betweene the lines.</p>
               <p>An Interlineall is either Contingent or Flat <hi>(m)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Contingent equalleth the distance betweene the lines in height. Of which sort are these among the Characters of Letters, <hi>(n)</hi> a c e i m n o r s u w z.</p>
               <p>A flatte, equalleth the distaunce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the lines in the length: as, — which is the note of Vnion. <hi>(o)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Transcendent, is a great Character, which extendeth it selfe further then the distance betweene the lines: And it pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth
<pb facs="tcp:5076:5"/> the bound of one line onely, or of both.</p>
               <p>Of one line onely, either the vpper, or the lower line.</p>
               <p>The vpper line: as, b d k l t.</p>
               <p>The lower line: as, g p q y.</p>
               <p>Of both: as</p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the first Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> Stenógraphie, signifieth a straightned or compendious Writing, by which name I call this Art, because all the preceptes thereof are directed therevnto: although it hath other profitable vses, as is before declared in the Proëme of this Booke.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> The Rules belonging to these two partes are seuerally deliuered in two Bookes. Those which concerne the abreuiation of a Word in the former, those which concerne the abreuiation of a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in the later.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(c)</hi> Character signifieth a Marke, Note, Impres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, Figure; written, engrauen, stampt, or howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer else made.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(d)</hi> All Characters are lineall, because they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist of lines continued: For euen the smallest tittle made with the Penne, hath his circumference, and consisteth of lines.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(e)</hi> That is to say, of any word, letter, number, name, clause, sentence, or whatsoeuer else.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(f)</hi> They are called Lineall notes of Letters, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb facs="tcp:5076:6"/> there are some notes of Letters, which are not Lineall, described by signes, not by draught of Pen: As, if a Towne strongly besieged be in great extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie for want of necessaries, and can not signifie the same to their friendes by any Messenger, all passages being kept by the Enemie, they may easily expresse their wantes to their friendes two myles off or more, euen in the darkest nyght (so that they also be acquainted with the order) in this manner. He which is to giue knowledge concerning the estate of the Towne, is to haue the matter whereof he is to giue intelligence written before him in as few wordes as may be: And euery letter written before him, he shall expresse in order by the lyfting vp of one, two, or three Torches lighted, in this wise. Let the Alphabet be deuided into three partes, each part conteyning 7. Letters a peece: of which the first 7. a b c d e f g, are to be expressed by the lyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp of one Torch onely, once for A, twice for B, thrice for C, foure times for D, fiue times for E, sixe times for F, seuen times for G. The second 7. which are, h i k l m n o, are to be expressed by the lifting vp of two Torches; once for H, twice for I, thrice for K, foure times for L, &amp;c. The thirde 7. to wit, p q r s t v w, are to be expressed by the lifting vp of three Torches; once for P, twice for Q, thrice for R, &amp;c. And by this meanes may any thing be signified in the night season, by lifting vp of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; and in the day time, by holding vp of Hattes, or such like; or neere at hand, by the Fingers. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Stratagem writeth WHITEHORNE in his Fireworks; and BAPTISTA PORTA de furt. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. notis. Letters also may be signified by tolling Belles, by
<pb facs="tcp:5076:6"/> shooting of Gunnes: or neere at hand, by any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument of musique.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(g)</hi> They are called Notes of letters rather then Letters, because euery Letter is perfect in it selfe by it proper sound, without respect of Character: For whereas Letters are ordinarily knowne three wayes; by the name whereby they are called, by the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter whereby they are written, and by the sounde whereby they are pronounced: Of these three, the sound or pronunciation is most essentiall to the letter. Therfore said PRISCIAN, <hi>Propter pronunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem &amp; figurae &amp; nomina literarum facta sunt:</hi> And hence it is, that the sound of a letter continueth the same in diuers languages, though it varie in name and Character; as the fourth Letter of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabet is in the Hebrew called <hi>Daleth,</hi> and written thus: In the Greeke called <hi>Delta,</hi> and written thus: In the Latin called <hi>Dee,</hi> &amp; written thus <hi>d:</hi> diuers names, and diuers Characters, but one letter; because pronounced with one sound.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(h)</hi> Parallell lines are those, which are euery whereof like distance one from another, as these are.<figure>
                        <figDesc>two parallel lines</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(i)</hi> Thwart, that is, lying crosse in respect of vs: For we are to write betweene these lines, from the left hand towardes the right, according to the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of writing vsed among vs, and not directly downewarde from the toppe to the bottome of the leafe (as the inhabitantes of CHINA are reported to doe. <hi>Pet. Math.</hi>) for these reasons. First, because it is easier for the Arme, which is lesse in motion when we write sideward, then when we write downeward. Secondly, because it lesse offendeth the eye, which
<pb facs="tcp:5076:7"/> with a glaunce readeth that which is written or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted crosse the leafe; but is wearied by often moouing vp and downe, to write or read from the top to the bottome of the leafe. Thirdly, for that writing side<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde is more speedily performed, by reason that more time is spent (though it be not marked) in moouing the arme to write downeward, then side<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Fourthly, by this meanes the Characters will be more seemely, and proportionable one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, being collaterally fitted and limited, in due measure by the lines: Lastly, this order of writing sideward, is more familiar vnto vs, then the other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(k)</hi> That is, whether the lines be Mathematicall and imaginatiue onely, or naturall and drawne with the penne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(l)</hi> Interlineall, signifieth that which is contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned betweene the lines. Transcendent, is that which passeth the boundes limitted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(m)</hi> Contingent, heere signifieth that which toucheth: and this name is giuen to Characters equalling the distance betweene the lines in height; because they touch the line onely at head and foote: And in such sence also is the worde Contingent vsed in Geometrie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(n)</hi> By this diuision of the Letters (which are heere set as examples to these Rules of great Characters) it is manifest, that the chiefe grace of writing stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the equall and euen proportionating of the interlineall Letters with the interlineall part of each Transcendent letter. And therefore, the spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall thing which good Schoole-maisters ayme at in teaching to write, is to make their Schollers know, which Letters are to be written wholly betweene
<pb facs="tcp:5076:7"/> the lines; and of the Transcendent letters, which is the interlineall part, and how to be fitted to the rest.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(o)</hi>—Is a Note placed betweene two wordes, sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying them to be vnited and knit into one: For which cause, it is called the note of Vnion: as, faire-seeming beautie, hard-harted enuie, selfe-tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting care.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Of small Characters. Chap. 2.</head>
               <p>A Small Character, occupieth lesse space then the distance betweene the lines, and is placed at some part of a great Character.</p>
               <p>A small Character is called, in respect of the place where it standeth, a <hi>Metaph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonge</hi> or an <hi>Aphthonge. (a)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Metaphthonge</hi> standeth in the place of a Vowell.</p>
               <p>The places of Vowels about Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters Contingent and Transcendent, are disposed thus.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:8"/>
               <p>The place of
<list>
                     <item>A at the foote and left side of a great Character.</item>
                     <item>E at the middle and left side of a great Character.</item>
                     <item>I at the head and left side of a great Character.</item>
                     <item>O at the head &amp; right side of a great Character.</item>
                     <item>V at the middle &amp; right side of a great Character.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The places of Vowels about flat Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, are thus disposed.</p>
               <p>The place of
<list>
                     <item>A beneath at the middle of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great Character.</item>
                     <item>E beneath at the left side of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great Character.</item>
                     <item>I aboue at the left side of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great Character.</item>
                     <item>O aboue at the middle of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great Character.</item>
                     <item>V aboue at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> right side of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great Character.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>An <hi>Aphthonge</hi> is a small Character, standing in a place where no Vowell is supposed to be: namely beneath at the right side of great Characters.</p>
               <p>Example of the places of both sortes of small Characters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout great <hi>(b)</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Contingent<figure>
                           <head>a e i o u</head>
                           <figDesc>vowels arranged about an upward arrow</figDesc>
                        </figure> Aphthonge.</item>
                     <item>Transcendent<figure>
                           <head>a e i o u</head>
                           <figDesc>vowels arranged about a vertical line</figDesc>
                        </figure> Aphthonge.</item>
                     <item>Flatte<figure>
                           <head>a e i o u</head>
                           <figDesc>vowels arranged about a horizontal line</figDesc>
                        </figure> Aphthonge.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, a small Character is either an Affix or a Disiunct.</p>
               <p>An Affix is a small Character ioyned to a great: as, <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> consisting of <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> consisting of — and ☉.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:8"/>
               <p>A Disiunct is a small Character disioyned from a great: as,</p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the second Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> Metaphthonge, signifieth either with a Vowel or after a Vowell: in both which significations, the worde doth fitly agree to small Characters stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the place of Vowels, because they do then consignifie a Vowell going before them. Aphthonge, signifieth Without a Vowell: by which name small Characters are styled, that haue no Vowell com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming before them in that place wherin they stand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> So that all small Characters standing in the place of the Vowels, a e i o u, are called Metaph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonges: standing in the sixt place, they are called Aphthonges.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:9"/>
               <head>CHAP. 3. Of Particles vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">1</cell>
                        <cell role="label">2</cell>
                        <cell role="label">3</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell>a.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>b.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>d.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>e.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>F</cell>
                        <cell>f.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>G</cell>
                        <cell>g. in good:</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>h.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>i. Vowell</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>l. Consonant. g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>k, c, q.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>l.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>m.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>n.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>o.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>π</cell>
                        <cell>p.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>q.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>r.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>s, c, t.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>T. in tyme.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>u. Vowell.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>v. Consonant.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>w.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>x.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>y.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>z.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>ch, in choice.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>AND so much concernyng the generall accidents of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters: <hi>(a)</hi> I will now descende into a more particular Narration of their vse in abreuiation of wordes.</p>
               <p>The Abreuia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of wordes by Characters, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth in two things: The Abreuiation of the partes of a word, &amp; the abre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiation of a whole word.</p>
               <p>The partes of a word, are letter &amp; syllable <hi>(b)</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:9"/>
               <p>A Letter <hi>(c)</hi> is abreuiated by taking a part thereof for the whole. And the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters so abreuiated, are called Particles.<hi>(d)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of Particles, some are vnchangeable, some changeable.</p>
               <p>An vnchangeable Particle is, whose sound is alwayes alike.</p>
               <p>And those are they, conteyned in the former Table: which consisteth of three columnes. The first sheweth which are the vnchangable Particles. The second, the Letters <hi>(e)</hi> whereof they are part. The third, sheweth what is their sound: where it is to be noted, that <hi>J</hi> the Consonant and <hi>g,</hi> being sounded as they are in these wordes <hi>(Iudge, gentle,)</hi> are to be expressed by the particle <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>K, C,</hi> and <hi>Q,</hi> being sounded as they are in these wordes <hi>(can, keepe, logique,)</hi> are to be expressed by <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>(f)</hi> s, c, t, being sounded as they are in these Wordes <hi>(his, face, nation)</hi> are to be written by <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> Also, the Particle <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> is euer sounded as g, in these wordes <hi>(good, graunt,)</hi>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> as t, in these wordes <hi>(tyme trieth trueth,)</hi>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> as ch, in these wordes <hi>(choice, chaunge:)</hi> The sounde of all the rest is manifest by the Table.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:10"/>
               <p>Of these Particles written at large, <hi>(g)</hi>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> is a Transcendent aboue the vpper line — ⌒  ͜  are Flattes: All the rest are Contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentes.</p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the third Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> Aswell illiterall as literall: For the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chapters concerne the common affections of both sortes of Characters.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> Ram. Gram. Lat. lib. pri. cap. tertio.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(c)</hi> A Letter is heere considered, not as it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by the sounde, but as it is written by his Character.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(d)</hi> Particle, signifieth a small part or portion of any thing: and in this Booke, that word for disti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction sake, is appropriate to letters abreuiated.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(e)</hi> Note that in this Table, ד and י are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred as partes to the Hebrew letters <hi>Daleth</hi> and <hi>Jod:</hi>
                     <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> χ to the Greeke letters <hi>Beta, My, pi, chi:</hi> and all the res<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o our vsuall letters. And they are thus referred, that they may be the better conteyned in memorie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(f)</hi> C In the English tongue, is noted to haue the sound of two letters K, and S. When it is soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as K, it is referred to K: When it is sounded as S, it is to be referred to S, and therefore hath heere no proper Particle.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(g)</hi> That is, extended to the boundes of great Characters.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:10"/>
               <head>Of changeable Particles. Chap. 4.</head>
               <p>A Changeable Particle, is a smal Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter whose sounde varieth. And of them there are two: to wit, o, and ◆ <hi>(a)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>o. Signifieth sometime H, sometime th. <hi>(b)</hi> It signifieth h, when it is affixed in the Aphthonge place of <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> as <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> Otherwise it signifieth th: as, <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>◆ Called a Tittle, is vsed either single, or dubble.</p>
               <p>When it is single, it noteth a Vowell: to wit, that Vowell in whose place it stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. So it signifieth a in the place of a, e in the place of e, i in the place of i, o in the place of o, u in the place of u, as: in <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> it standeth for a, in <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> it standeth for e, in <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> it standeth for i, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>A Tittle dubbled, signifieth the plurall number, when they are placed in this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (<seg rend="sup">··</seg>) at the head of a Character, as: hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites. <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5076:11"/>
                  <head>Notes vpon the fourth Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> O, May be referred to <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as a part thereof. A tittle may indifferently be referred to any Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, as the smallest part thereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> The reason of the Rule is this. Aspirable letters, that is, such as are capable of H, to be ioyned with them immediately in the same Syllable, are either Vowels or Consonantes. The Vowels are all aspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and haue their Aspiration alwayes going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, as: hand, heere, hill, hope, humble: sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in these Interiections Ah, Oh: In which two, the Aspiration following is neglected by a Rule Chap 6. Of the Consonantes 7. onely are aspirable which are these, C, G, P, R, S, T, W: and these haue their Aspiration following them, as. Chaffe, Ghoste, Phisicke, Rhewme. Short, Thinke, When. Of these C aspirated, hath his proper Character X. Gh, and Rh, neglect their aspirations by a Rule Chapt 6. Ph, is contracted into F: So that onely S, T, and, W, neede to haue H thus expressed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:11"/>
               <head>Of Vowels neglected. Chap. 5.</head>
               <p>ANd thus much concerning the abre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiation of Letters: the abreuiation of a Syllable followeth. <hi>(a)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Syllable is abreuiated in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guarde either of the sounde whereby it is pronounced, or of the Character where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it is written.</p>
               <p>In reguarde of the sounde, either by omission or contraction of some part thereof.</p>
               <p>A Syllable abreuiated by omission of some part thereof, hath that part omitted, either neglected, or vnderstood.</p>
               <p>The part of a Syllable neglected, is Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well or Consonant.</p>
               <p>A Vowell is neglected: First, when it serueth onely to lengthen the sounde of a Vowell next before going: Immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arely, as: espie. Or, mediately, <hi>(b)</hi> as: Oates, more.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:12"/>
               <p>Secondly, when more Vowels are soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded togither in one Syllable, as in a Diph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonge or a Triphthonge.</p>
               <p>A Diphthonge is a sound of two Vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els in one Syllable: and of them there are twentie, that is to say,</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>ai, raine.</item>
                     <item>ay, may.</item>
                     <item>au, laude</item>
                     <item>aw, saw.</item>
                     <item>ea, heate</item>
                     <item>ee, thee.</item>
                     <item>ei, either.</item>
                     <item>ey, obey.</item>
                     <item>eo, ieopard.</item>
                     <item>eu, leude.</item>
                     <item>ew, few.</item>
                     <item>ie, chiefe.</item>
                     <item>oa, loade.</item>
                     <item>oe, phoenix.</item>
                     <item>oi, hoist.</item>
                     <item>oy, annoy.</item>
                     <item>oo, good.</item>
                     <item>ou, bound.</item>
                     <item>ow, sow.</item>
                     <item>ui, suite.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>A triphthonge is a sound of three Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels in one syllable: And of them there are fiue, to wit,</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>aoi, Gaoill.</item>
                     <item>eau, Beautie.</item>
                     <item>eaw, Deaw.</item>
                     <item>ieu, Lieu.</item>
                     <item>iew, View.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Euery of these aforesaid Polyphthonges is to be expressed by that onely Vowel, which is most sounded in it, as,
<list>
                     <item>ai, ay, au, aw, aoi. are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed by A</item>
                     <item>ea, ee, eo, oe. are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed by E</item>
                     <item>ie, ei, ey. are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed by I</item>
                     <item>oa, oi, oy, ou, ow. are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed by O</item>
                     <item>eu, ew, eaw, eau, ieu, iew, ui. are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed by V</item>
                  </list> Except their other Vowell be most sounded, which very seldome falleth out, as: in these words, heart, youth</p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5076:12"/>
                  <head>Notes vpon the fifth Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> A Syllable is heere handled as it is properly so called, namely as consisting of more letters then one: for the Vowels pronounced alone, are improperly called Syllabels, because the word Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable signifieth a taking togither, to wit, of more letters into one sound.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> That is, a Consonant comming betweene.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(c)</hi> Phthongos in Greeke, signifieth a Vowell. Diphthongos, two Vowels. Triphthongos, three Vowels in one Syllable.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Consonantes neglected. Chap. 6.</head>
               <p>A Consonant is neglected: first, when it commeth before an other Conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the same sounde, <hi>(a)</hi> as: all, assure, ascend, acquit, follow, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge.</p>
               <p>Secondly, when it is added to another Consonant to thicken the sound thereof. Such are these in these wordes, and the like.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5076:13"/>
                  <item>B, Chamblet, debt, lambe.</item>
                  <item>C, Annoynted.</item>
                  <item>D, Iudge.</item>
                  <item>G, Raigne, gnibble.</item>
                  <item>L, Realme, balme.</item>
                  <item>P, Dampson, Psalme, exempt, accompt.</item>
                  <item>Pn, p Solempne.</item>
                  <item>T, Wretch.</item>
                  <item>V, The liquid, <hi>(b)</hi> build, question.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Thirdly, when the sound therof is drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as in these, and such like.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>C, Sclaunder, excell, victuall.</item>
                  <item>D, Rundlet, kindled, adiourne.</item>
                  <item>G, Strength, yonglinges.</item>
                  <item>L, Salmon.</item>
                  <item>N, Damne.</item>
                  <item>P, Vpbrayd, Cupboard.</item>
                  <item>T, Mortgage.</item>
                  <item>Th, Rythme.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Fourthly, Aspirations are neglected, <hi>(c) Viz.</hi> First, light Aspirations, which are H. W. Y. and that either when they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect a Vowell in the middle of a word; as: Vehement, Abhorre, Bulwarke, Beyonde.</p>
               <p>Or, when the letter which they affect, hath his sounde nothing chaunged by the Aspiration: as; Ghost, Christopher, Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torique, Arthur, Thomas, Wreake, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray,
<pb facs="tcp:5076:13"/> Youth, You, Humble, Husher.</p>
               <p>Secondly, a thicke Aspiration, either gh, when it followeth a Vowel in the same Syllable: as; Though, Night, Burrough.</p>
               <p>Or, H alone in these Interiections <hi>(d)</hi> Ah, Oh.</p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the 6. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> So in the word (Ascende) <hi>S</hi> and C, are of the same sounde, though different letters: As on the other side, in the word (Suggestion) gg, in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, are the same letter, though different in sounde: and therefore these wordes are vsed in the precept <hi>Consonantes of the same sounde,</hi> not Consonantes of the same letter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> When in ui, the sounde of u, is more heard then i. ui is a Diphthong, as in these wordes; suite, fruite. But when the sound of i is chiefest, u is a Liquid, as in the wordes; Build, guile.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(c)</hi> There are in the English tongue 4. Aspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, H, W, Y, Gh: which yet are numbred among the Consonantes, <hi>quia consonant, hoc est, cum voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus sonant:</hi> for euen W and Y, are in nature As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirations, though abusiuely written in Diphthongs for i and u.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(d)</hi> For in these wordes, H, hath the strength of a thicke Aspiration, as if they were thus writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, Agh, Ogh.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:14"/>
               <head>Of Vowels vnderstood. Chap. 7.</head>
               <p>THe part of a Syllable omitted, yet vnderstoode, is a Vowell: to wit,</p>
               <p>First, E before X in the beginning of a word, <hi>(a)</hi> as: xchange, xtreeme, for exchange, extreeme.</p>
               <p>Secondly, all middle and finall Vowels. For these are vnderstood by the Metaph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonges standing in their place, <hi>(b)</hi> as: in <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Metaphthonge <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> affixed to <hi>C</hi> in the place of <hi>I,</hi> sheweth the Vowell <hi>I</hi> to go before it: In <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> the disiunct Metaph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonge (<gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>) signifieth the Vowell <hi>O,</hi> in whose place it standeth.</p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the seauenth Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> E before X, omitted in the beginning of a word, may well be vnderstood, both because no English word beginneth with X, as also for that E being remooued, X cannot so fully be pronounced without the sounde of E short vnderheard before it: as in the former examples, xchange, xtreeme, being pronounced, the sound of E short, is heard before them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> For Metaphthonges do alwayes consignifie the same Vowell to goe before them in the place whereof they stand. Chapt. 10. and 11.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:14"/>
               <head>Of Letters Contracted. Chap. 8.</head>
               <p>SO much concerning the abreuiation of a Syllable, by omitting some part thereof.</p>
               <p>A Syllable is abreuiated by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, when the sound of two, or more Letters is contracted into one: as in these wordes following, and the like. <hi>(a)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>ao in Sabaoth is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted into O.</item>
                     <item>ia in Triacle is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted into E.</item>
                     <item>hi in Hierome is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted into I, the consonant</item>
                     <item>cc in Accesse is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted into X.</item>
                     <item>ct in Fiction is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted into X.</item>
                     <item>ckes in Trickes is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted into X.</item>
                     <item>ph in phantasie is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted into F.</item>
                     <item>que in Antique is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted into C, or Q.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the 8. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> In this Art, not the Orthographie, but the sound of the word is respected. And for such con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of Letters by the sound, we haue the presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of Antiquitie to warrant it. First in the time of the Troian warre Palamedes added 4. Letters
<pb facs="tcp:5076:15"/> to the Greeke Alphabet <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> which are made of doubble soundes, <hi>viz.</hi> th, ph, ch: and ξ of ps, gs, and chs. And after him, <hi>Simonides</hi> taking the like libertie, added other 4. Characters of Letters contracted in like maner, <hi>viz. z</hi> for fs and ds: <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> for ec: ψ for bs, ps, phs: and <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> for oo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Suetonius</hi> also writeth, that <hi>Augustus Caesar</hi> added X and Z, to the number of Lattine letters: Z, for ss, which is worne out of vse: and X for Cs, which is still in vse. So, for <hi>Alecsander</hi> (so written before <hi>Augustus</hi> time) we write <hi>Alexander:</hi> for Ecsamen, Examen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the abreuiation of affixed Particles. Chap. 9.</head>
               <p>THus much for the abreuiation of a Syllable, in reguarde of the sounde thereof: Now, how a Syllable is abreuiated, in respect of his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter.</p>
               <p>A Syllable is abreuiated in respect of the Character wherewith it is written, when the small Particle may be conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently vnderstood by some part thereof af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed to the great, or to such a small Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle
<pb facs="tcp:5076:15"/> as is vnto it in nature of a great.</p>
               <p>Affixed to a great, as, <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> consisting of <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> consisting of <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>(a)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Affixed to such a small Particle, as is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it in nature of a great, <hi>(b)</hi> as, <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> consist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> — and <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the .9. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> This kind of abreuiation, we finde to be vsed both in Greeke and Latin, and other languages: as, oe, ae, sl.</p>
                  <p>Heere for a plaine direction how euery small Particle is to be affixed to a great in his due place, as any man diligently obseruing these Rules, may frame vnto himselfe a Table, which in a short view may readily declare the same: So there is a very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Table already drawne to that purpose, where vnto the Printer can direct him, that is desirous thereof, for his ease and satisfaction.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> For a small Particle, as it is the subiect where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto an other small Particle is affixed, hath the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of a great Character, being compared vnto it: as in the examples propounded. <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> is a great Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, in respect of — affixed to it, and — is as a great Particle in respect of <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> affixed to it,</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:16"/>
               <head>Of Wordes of one Syllable. Chap. 10.</head>
               <p>HAuing declared how the partes of a word are abreuiated, it remaineth to shew the abreuiation of a whole word.</p>
               <p>A word abreuiated, is expressed by a note either Homogeneall, or Heteroge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall. <hi>(a)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A note Homogeneall, is that which is written by one or more Characters of one kinde, <hi>(b)</hi> and it is either Literall or Illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall.</p>
               <p>A Literall, is a note expressed by literall Character, <hi>(c)</hi> and it is either Integrall or Defectiue.</p>
               <p>An Integrall, is a note expressing by particles all the needfull <hi>(d)</hi> letters of a word; and the first letter by a great Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle.</p>
               <p>How Wordes are to be written by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrals, let vs now consider.</p>
               <p>A Word, consisteth either of one Sylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or of more Syllables then one.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:16"/>
               <p>A Word of one Syllable, beginneth ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a Vowell, or with a Consonant.</p>
               <p>If it begin with a Vowel, the Consonant or Consonants following, are to be placed in their order <hi>(e)</hi> by Aphthonge <gap reason="symbol" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>〈☐☐☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> affix. as: are, arme, armes.</p>
               <p>If it be a Consonant, marke whether the Syllable doth ende in a Vowel or in a Consonant.</p>
               <p>If it ende in a Vowel, the Vowel is to be expressed by a Tittle standing in the place thereof. And if any Consonant or Consonants come betweene, they are to be expressed in their order by Aphthonge Affix. as: doe, trew, through.</p>
               <p>If it ende in a Consonant, the Conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is to be expressed by his small particle affixed in the place of the Vowell going before it: And if there be any more Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonantes in the Syllable, they are to be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in their order, <hi>(f)</hi> as: Bad, light, with, chaunge, brought.</p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the 10. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> Homogeneall signifieth, of the same kinde or sort: Heterogeneall, of an other kinde or sort.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> As when it is written onely by Particle, or
<pb facs="tcp:5076:17"/> by an ordinarie Letter, or by an Illiterall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(c)</hi> Whether it be an ordinarie Letter, or a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle: For the Characters of both these sortes are literall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(d)</hi> What are the needfull Letters of euery word, sufficiently appeareth by the abreuiation of Sylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles before touch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d in this Booke.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(e)</hi> That is, the Particle of euery Letter must be affixed in the Aphthonge place of the Particle of that l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tter which goeth next before it. as in the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd Armes, r is affixed to a in the Aphthonge place thereof: m is affixed to r in Aphthonge place of r: and s to m in the Aphthonge place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f m.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(f)</hi> That is, those which goe before the Vowel, are to be affixed orderly in the Aphthonge place, and those which come after the Vowell orderly in the Metaphthonge place.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>Of wordes of more Syllables. Chapt. 11.</head>
               <p>WHen we write a worde of more Syllables, we must consider the improper partes thereof. <hi>(a)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An improper part of a word of more Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lables, is either Primarie or Secundarie.</p>
               <p>The Primarie part, conteyneth the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or letters comming before the seconde
<pb facs="tcp:5076:17"/> Vowell▪ as; in <hi>Io,</hi> the primarie part is <hi>I:</hi> in <hi>Ida, Id:</hi> in <hi>Abroad, Abr:</hi> in <hi>Fauour, Fau.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The secundarie part contayneth the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Vowell with the Letter or Letters following, if there be any: as; in <hi>Chw,</hi> the secundarie part is <hi>o:</hi> in <hi>Occidente,</hi> the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundarie part is <hi>idente:</hi> in <hi>Calumniation, umniation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heere note, that two Vowels comming togither, not in the beginning of the word, are to be expressed with their Consonant or Consonants, if any follow, as if they were but one Syllable; to wir, the Particle of the later affixed with his Consonant or Consonants, if there be any, in the place of the former Vowell: as, <hi>Rhea, Chloë, Lewes.</hi>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>〈☐☐☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>The primarie part of a Word is to be expressed as a Word of one syllable. <hi>(b)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Secundarie part, consisteth either onely of a Vowell, or of more Letters.</p>
               <p>If it consist of a Vowell only, that Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well is to be expressed by a Tittle stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the place thereof: as; <hi>Arrowe, Armie, Duetie.</hi>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>〈☐☐☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>If it consist of more letters, it may be written more wayes then one: <hi>(c)</hi> to wit,
<pb facs="tcp:5076:18"/> by some, or all of these foure wayes follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing.</p>
               <p>First, by Metaphthonge, referred onely to the great Particle <hi>(d)</hi> affixed onely, as in these, <hi>Abridge, Accorde, Asia, Eoas.</hi>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>〈☐☐☐☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>Affixed and disioyned: as, <hi>Obl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>quie, Aeolia, Barren.</hi>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>〈☐☐☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, by Metaphthonge affixed to a small Particle: which small Particle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specteth the great, either as an affix <gap reason="symbol" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>〈☐☐☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> as; <hi>Arthur, Daughter, Currente.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or, as a Disiunct, as; <hi>Seperate, Glorious.</hi>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>〈☐☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, by Disiunctes, whose Vowels come each after other according to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Alphabet, as; <hi>Lion,</hi>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>〈☐☐☐☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Glorious, Superior, Clio, Paradice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, by collaterall <hi>(e)</hi> great Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles affixed or accompanied with dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctes as if they were seuerall Wordes, yet ioyned closer togither then seuerall Wordes: as; <hi>Lionesse, Perturbation, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropophagite.</hi>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>〈☐☐☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>(f)</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5076:18"/>
                  <head>Notes vpon the 11. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> These are called the Improper partes of a Word: as for the Proper partes of a Word, they are Letter and Syllable. Chapt. 3.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> That is, according to the Rules deliuered in Chapter next before going.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(c)</hi> As the word <hi>Lionesse,</hi> which may be written 12. seuerall wayes by the Rules of this Booke, <hi>Viz.</hi>
                     <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>But in this, and all other Wordes which is the play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest and easiest way to write them, may better be learned by practise then precept.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(d)</hi> The Disiunctes mentioned in the third Rule, are Metaphthonges, referred to the great Particle: but not onely vnto it, for they are also referred to the Vowell of the Disiunct next going before.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(e)</hi> Collaterall, that is placed side by side: as in our vsuall wryting one Letter is placed by the side of another in due proportion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(f)</hi> So that by the Rules of these two last Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, is declared how any Word whatsoeuer, may be fully written. And though to place Disiunctes abdue great Characters in wordes of many Syllables, might seeme to breede confusion; yet therein will appeare no trouble at all: for, we write Hebrew wordes with small Characters, and Prickes aboue, beneath, on the side, or within the Letters; which yet are not thought to bring confusion, but great helpe to the Reader: But if any inconuenience should arise thereof, it may easily be redressed by the fourth Rule of this Chapter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:19"/>
               <head>Of the first part of Defectiues. Chapt. 12.</head>
               <p>IT hath been declared how all Wordes may be expressed by Integrall notes: Let vs now see how some Wordes may be expressed by Defectiues.</p>
               <p>A Defectiue, is a Literall note of a word, wanting one or more of the neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Letters thereof.</p>
               <p>Of Defectiues there are foure sortes.</p>
               <p>The first, is of them which note so much of a word, as is sufficient to distinguish it from all other wordes: as, <hi>(a) (b)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>First, <hi>Baptisme, Apothecarie, Nothing, Whither.</hi>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>〈☐☐☐☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Augustine, Pionie, Brewer, Gouernour.</hi>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>〈☐☐☐☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5076:19"/>
                  <head>Notes vpon the 12. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> The first sort of Defectiues, includeth as well all Wordes, hauing a peculiar beginning by themselues (such as are the former three, and many more, which practise will disc uer) as also them, which want some Letters, betweene the first and the last: such as are the other foure, and the like.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> These kindes of abridgement, are both of them often vsed by Notaries: as; <hi>Mnu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>' Manuce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perunt. Vis. Franc. pleg. Visus franci p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>egij. ce in miā. esse in misericordia. Cur Sccij. Curia Scaccarij. firm̄r. firmiter. heret. haberet. Abs{que} disparag. absque dispa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragatione.</hi> Such is also the abridgement of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours name vsed formerly by the Greekes: For in steed of <gap reason="foreign" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> they wrote ΙΗS ΧΡS wherein it is to be noted, that ΗΧΡ. are not Latine letters (as some suppose) but the Greeke letters <hi>Eta, Chi, Rho.</hi> The mistaking whereof, caused that errour of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting IHS, for IESVS: XP, for CHRIST: Xpofer, for Christopher: Xpiān, for Christian, and such like.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:20"/>
               <head>Of the second sort of Defectiues. Chapt. 13.</head>
               <p>THe second sort of Defectiues, is of them which expresse the first or last syllable of a word, by a single dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunct Aphthonge, placed either Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly, or Irregularly.</p>
               <p>Regularly, <hi>(a)</hi> And then they note the last syllable, either by the first letter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: As in wordes of these terminations following.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>And, as, Command.</item>
                  <item>By, as, Whereby.</item>
                  <item>Call, as, Tragicall.</item>
                  <item>Dome, as, Wisedome.</item>
                  <item>Els, as, Bowels.</item>
                  <item>Full, as, Sinfull.</item>
                  <item>Ger, as, Longer.</item>
                  <item>Iect, as, Obiect.</item>
                  <item>Lesle, as, Friendlesse</item>
                  <item>Man, as, Workman.</item>
                  <item>Nesse, as, Bouldnesse.</item>
                  <item>Olde, as, Harolde.</item>
                  <item>Parte, as, Depart.</item>
                  <item>Ringe, as, Alluringe.</item>
                  <item>So, as, Also.</item>
                  <item>To, as, Hitherto.</item>
                  <item>Vert, as, Peruerte.</item>
                  <item>Vse, as, misuse.</item>
                  <item>Ward, as, Froward.</item>
                  <item>The, as, Lethe.</item>
                  <item>It, as, Vnit.</item>
                  <item>If, as, Plaintiffe.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Or by the last Letter thereof, as in words of these terminations following.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5076:20"/>
                  <item>Lique, as, Catholique.</item>
                  <item>Lie, as, Vainelie.</item>
                  <item>Ish, as, Cherish.</item>
                  <item>Az, as, Paraz.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Aphthongs placed Irregularlie, that is, vnder the great Particle of the letter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing at the left side thereof, note the first Syllable, <hi>(b)</hi> by the first Letter: As first, in words beginning with Re. as, Resigne. Secondly, in wordes beginning with any of these Syllables following.</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Em, as, Emperour.</item>
                     <item>Im, as, Impure.</item>
                     <item>En, as, Enioy.</item>
                     <item>In, as, Indicte.</item>
                     <item>Vn, as, Vnneath.</item>
                     <item>Il before L, as, Illumine.</item>
                     <item>Ir before R, as, Irreuerend</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>In which syllables the first letter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Vowell is to be expressed by a tittle. <hi>(c)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in flat Characters, <hi>(d)</hi> the place for Aphthonges beginning the word is at the left side: and for Aphthonges ending the word at the right side thereof, as,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                        </gap> Require.</item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                        </gap> Enriched.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the .13. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> That is, in the Aphthonge place.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> This is an exception against the First Rule of
<pb facs="tcp:5076:21"/> the 11. Chapter, which requireth that the first letter of a word should be expressed by a great Particle. Where note, that onely the Particle —and <seg rend="sup">m</seg>iddot; are to be vsed for first Syllables, because they take vp no roome vnder the great Character, as other Particles would, if they were so vsed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(c)</hi> Which is an indefenite Character of a vowel.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(d)</hi> The reason of this exception, is because in flat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Characters, the place of E is beneath at the left side, Chapt. 2. and the place for Notes of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction, is beneath at the right side. Chapt. 3. of the second Booke.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the third sort of Defectiues. Chapt. 14.</head>
               <p>THe thirde sort of Defectiues, is of them which expresse a word by the first Letter onely. <hi>(a)</hi> To wit, either by a Particle, or an ordinarie Letter.</p>
               <p>By a Particle, so are these Wordes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed.</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>But.</item>
                     <item>Come.</item>
                     <item>Dis.</item>
                     <item>For.</item>
                     <item>God.</item>
                     <item>He.</item>
                     <item>Iesus.</item>
                     <item>Let.</item>
                     <item>Make.</item>
                     <item>Not.</item>
                     <item>Of.</item>
                     <item>Pro.</item>
                     <item>Quest.</item>
                     <item>Rich.</item>
                     <item>Sub.</item>
                     <item>That.</item>
                     <item>Rent.</item>
                     <item>Which</item>
                     <item>Xcepte.</item>
                     <item>Yet.</item>
                     <item>Christ.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>A word noted by an ordinarie Letter, is noted either by a small Letter, or by a Capitall.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:21"/>
               <p>By a small letter either Romaine or Secretarie.</p>
               <p>Words written by small Romaine let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, are these.</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Againe.</item>
                     <item>because.</item>
                     <item>cause.</item>
                     <item>doctrine</item>
                     <item>euer.</item>
                     <item>father.</item>
                     <item>gospell.</item>
                     <item>hypocrite</item>
                     <item>interre.</item>
                     <item>kneele.</item>
                     <item>lente.</item>
                     <item>much.</item>
                     <item>neuer.</item>
                     <item>ouer.</item>
                     <item>pouertie.</item>
                     <item>queene.</item>
                     <item>reguard.</item>
                     <item>such.</item>
                     <item>traunce.</item>
                     <item>vengeance.</item>
                     <item>vnto.</item>
                     <item>would.</item>
                     <item>xtreeme</item>
                     <item>yeere.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Wordes written by small Secretarie letters, are these.</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Among.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>before.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>can.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>declare</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>earth.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>friende.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>great.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hereti{que}</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>kinde.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lord.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>mercy.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>name.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>other</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>part.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>quaint.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>repent.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>serue.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>selfe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>therefore.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>se.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>vpon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>vvicked.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>xperience.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>young.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Wordes written by Capitall letters, are written either by Romaine Capitals, or by Secretarie.</p>
               <p>By Romaine Capitalles, Solitarie, or Combined.</p>
               <p>Solitarie: as, A. Apostle, D. Deute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronomie, H. Hebrewes, K. Kinges, L. Lamentations, Marke, Numbers, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbes, Reuelation. <hi>(b)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Romane Capitals combined, signifie two names or wordes in one: as, <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> Hermes Trismegistus. <hi>(c)</hi>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> Councell of Constance. <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap> Acte of Parliament.</p>
               <p>Wordes written by Secretarie Capitals: as, E. Euangelist, P. Prophet. <hi>(d)</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5076:22"/>
                  <head>Notes vpon the .14. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> The writing of the first letter for the whole worde, is a very auncient kind of abreuiation: For before the time of <hi>Iustinian</hi> the Emperour, the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries and Registers of the Law were wont for more speed in wryting, oft times to write onely the first letter for a worde: as, <hi>L. P. Latini Prisci. L. I. Lex Iulia D A.C De adulteriis coë<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cendis. C E C Coloni eius Colmie. V. B A Viriboni arbitratu. Q.R.F.E.V. Quod recte fictum esse videbitur. &amp;c. Valer. Probus de Romanorum notis.</hi> These Abreuiations were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Sig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a, (quasi singl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> per Syncopen pro S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ngula, vt veteres viglas pro vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lia, dixisse feruntur. Instit. lib.</hi> 1.) And as they vsed them, it bred no little confusion, because they vsed the same letter for many words: as; <hi>A</hi> for <hi>Aulus, age<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, aut, annus, aliu, aio, &amp;c.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many by craftinesse of witte, interpreted the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters contrary to the meaning of the Law, thereby abusing the simple and ignoraunt: Which abuse, <hi>Iustinian</hi> willing to reforme, commaunded from thence forwarde vnder a penaltie, that none should vse those Abreuiations. Such Abreuiatures also of a letter for a word haue been and are vsed in monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, noting names and tittles, in computati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and accomptes, and such like affayres. So we reade that <hi>Ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> finding in a monument of Stone these Greeke letters <gap reason="foreign" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> interpreted the Greeke wordes by their first letters in this significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>Goe forward, foure paces, digge, thou shalt finde a treasure of golde: Aesop</hi> did so, and found a Potte
<pb facs="tcp:5076:22"/> of Gold. So when <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth was created <hi>Pope,</hi> one set vp this Libel vpon the Pasquil, <hi>M. C C. C. C. L. D.</hi> Which numerall letters the Authour himselfe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poūded t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s: <hi>Multi Cardinales caeci creauerunt caecum Leonem Decimum:</hi> that is, Many blinde Cardinals created a blind Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth Likewise in the inscription of the Collar which the Knights of the order of the Salutation weare, these letters, <hi>F.E. R.T.</hi> stand for, <hi>Fortitudo eius Rhodum tenuit:</hi> His prowesse kept <hi>Rhodes:</hi> Meaning, the Prowesse of <hi>Amadeus</hi> the sixt, Earle of <hi>Sauoie,</hi> who defended <hi>Rhodes</hi> against the <hi>Turke,</hi> and in memorie thereof, instituted this order. Such kind of Abreuiations are some time also vsed among vs: as; <hi>E R. Elizabetha Regina. C. S. Custos Sigilli. A. D. Anno Domini &amp;c.</hi> And such are the defectiues contayned in this Chapter: wherein I haue referred no more then one vsuall Word to one Character, for auoyding confusion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> These wordes in this Chapter are so assigned to Particles and Letters, as I leaue it indifferent to any to vse these wordes, or other in their steade: because with Diuines some wordes are more vsuall, with Lawyers other wordes, with Physitians other, with Poets other. &amp;c. And therefore I haue heere, and in the Defectiues of the Chapter following, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giuen instance of my meaning in one or two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, referring it to their choyce, what wordes they shall thinke best to expresse by these defectiue Notes, according to the seuerall subiect of their Studie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(c)</hi> compounded of <hi>H.</hi> and <hi>T,</hi> the two first Letters of the name and firname of <hi>Hermes Tris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megistus,</hi> a famous King of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5076:23"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(d)</hi> Although I haue giuen example onely of the Romaine and Secretarie letters, as being most vsuall: yet the Letters of other Handes also may profitably be vsed to signifie wordes; as, <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> Court, <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> Malefactor, <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> Sraunge, <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> ment.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the fourth sort of Defectiues. Chap. 15.</head>
               <p>THe fourth sort of Defectiues, is of them which expresse onely two let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Word by an Aphthonge particle affixed to a great, and it expresseth either the two first Letters, or the first and the last.</p>
               <p>The two first, regularly, or irregularly.</p>
               <p>Regularly, <hi>(b)</hi> as; <hi>Abounde, after, from, place, shall, this,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="symbol" extent="9 letters">
                        <desc>〈9 letters〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>what, stande, answere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Irregularly, <hi>(c)</hi> as: <hi>Multitude,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="symbol" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>〈☐☐☐☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Mediate, Posteritie, Necessarie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Defectiues, expressing the first and last Letter, are to haue such Wordes referred to them as either begin and ende with a
<pb facs="tcp:5076:23"/> Vowel: as also. Or if they begin and ende with a Consonant; the last Consonant is such, as neuer followeth immediately the first in the beginning of an English word, <hi>(d)</hi> as: <hi>Difference, Meruaile, Respect.</hi>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>〈☐☐☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>Note, that many Words may fitly be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed according to these former Rules <hi>(e)</hi> by Notes defectiue, in more respectes then one: as; <hi>Faythfulnesse, Ʋntowardnesse, Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliable, Proiecte.</hi>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>〈☐☐☐☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the 15. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> So the Romaines expressed many Wordes by two or three of their first Letters: as, <hi>Tr, Pl, Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Plehis. Ag. Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t Ac, Actio. Eq, Equiria. Gl. Gloria. Arm, Armilustrium. Car, carmentalia. Rob Robiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia. &amp;c.</hi> Which also is vsed in the Canon Law: as, <hi>Se. ap. Sedes Apostolica. Sa. ap con. Sacro approbante concilio. Pur cano. De purgatione canonica.</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise they sometime wrote a worde by the first and last letter thereof: as, <hi>Dt.</hi> for <hi>Duntaxat. Qm. Quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum. ee. esse.</hi> as we vsually write <hi>Lr.</hi> for <hi>Letter, Dd.</hi> for <hi>Deliuered.</hi> and <hi>Mr.</hi> for <hi>Maister.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> That is, expressed according to the Rules be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deliuered, the second Letter being a Conso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant affixed to the first, in the Aphthonge place thereof.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5076:24"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(c)</hi> That is, by affixing the second Letter, being a Vowell, to the first Letter in the Aphthonge place thereof, contrary to the former Rules: whereby it is required that the second Letter being a Vowell, should be vnderstood by a Metaphthonge Chap. 11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(d)</hi> As in the examples giuen, no English word beginneth with ds, ml. rt: And heere note, that in other Languages, many wordes begin with such Letters, as no word in the Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sh tongue begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth withall: as; <hi>bdella, ctesis, pneuma, Mneme, Sphinx, Sbesis, Tlao, tmolus,</hi> in the Greeke: <hi>Lluellyn</hi> in the British <hi>Vlishing &amp;c.</hi> Notwithstanding, seeing no English word beginneth with the same Letters, euen the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e may passe for Defectiue notes with the rest: as; <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> beside <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> mention.</p>
                  <p>Heere further marke, that all the Defectiue notes, intreated of in these two last Chapters the xiiij and the xv. may be very well reduced into a Table: (the manner how, is apparant by the Rules.) vnto which the Reader may referre what wordes he thinketh best; yet with this regard, that they be wordes vsuall vnto himselfe: or such as being fully written, would be vnhandsome. Which when he hath done, he shall not need to get the wordes of the Table by hare, but by remembring vnto what kinde of defectiues the word is referred; the Rule it selfe sheweth how the word is to be written. As if I remember that the word <hi>Meruaile</hi> is placed among the Defectiues, written by the first and last letter, I know by the Rule, that it must be expressed by the Aphthonge particle of the last letter affixed to the first.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:24"/>
               <head>Of Illiterals. Chap. 16.</head>
               <p>HItherto concerning literal Characterst it followeth to speake of the Illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals.</p>
               <p>An Illiterall, is a Character hauing the same signification in all Languages. <hi>(a)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of which sort are, First Characters Arithmeticall, <hi>(b)</hi> 1. 2. 3. 4 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 0. By which tenne Characters, varied by place and position, <hi>(c)</hi> all numbers whole and broken, are to be expressed, according to the rules of Arithmetique.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Characters Astronomicall: as,</p>
               <p n="1">1. of the Planets, <hi>(d)</hi> ♄ Saturne, ♃ Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter, ♂ Mars, ☉ Sunne, ♀ Venus, ☿ Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie, ☽ Moone.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of the twelue Signes in the Zodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acke, <hi>(e)</hi> ♈ Ramme, ♉ Bull, ♊ Twinne, ♋ Crabbe, ♌ Lion, ♍ Virgin, ♎ Ballance, ♏ Scorpion, ♐ Archer, ♑ Goate, ♒ Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terman, ♓ Fishes.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Characters vsed in Bookes of the Ciuil Law § Paragraph, ff Digectes <hi>(f)</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5076:25"/>
                  <head>Notes vpon the .16. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> As the Character ☉ signifieth in English the Sunne, in Latine <hi>Sol,</hi> in Greeke <hi>Helios,</hi> in Hebrew <hi>Schemesh,</hi> in French <hi>Soleil. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> The auncient Hebrewes and Greekes, as also the Pythagoreans in their diuinations by Onoman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, vsed all the letters of the Alphabet as Numerals. The Romaines ordinarily vsed these seauen to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse numbers by, C. D. I. L. M. V. X, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ∽ for 200. S for 1000. <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> for 100000. {roman 1000000} for 1000000. &amp;c. <hi>Ʋal Prob.</hi> But the tenne Figures of Arithmetique, inuented (as is supposed) by the <hi>Arabians,</hi> are by the agreement almost of all Nations, reputed to be the most fitte for expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing all manner of Numbers. <hi>Joac. Camer. de Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistica.</hi> The Characters vsed in Cossicke numbers, I omit; because their vse is not so common as the rest.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(c)</hi> Varied by place, as in whole Numbers; and those which are <hi>Quasi Integra: Ʋrstitius.</hi> Varied by position, as in Fractions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(d)</hi> ♄ Is the Character of <hi>Saturne,</hi> either because by the crookednes thereof it resembleth aged <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> bowed with yeeres (<hi>Saturnus enim dicitur, quod saturetur annis. Cic. de Nat. deor. lib.</hi> 2.) Or els because it is like a Sith, which <hi>Saturne</hi> is fayned to carry in his hand, in signification that Time cutteth off the course of all mens liues: for <hi>Saturne</hi> is called in the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>quasi</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign" extent="3 words">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> which signifieth Time. ♃ is the Character of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> for that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presenteth a Scepter, such as <hi>Iupiter</hi> is supposed to
<pb facs="tcp:5076:25"/> beare. ♂ is the Character of <hi>Mars,</hi> because it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presenteth a Clubbe and an Arrow; weapons vsed in Warre: for <hi>Mars</hi> among the Heathen was counted Patron of Warre. ☉ is the Character of the Sunne, representing the roundnesse of the body, and the brightnesse of the beames of the Sunne. ♀ is the Character of <hi>Ʋenus,</hi> hauing the forme of a looking Glasse, which <hi>Ʋenus</hi> holdeth in her hand. ☿ is the Character of <hi>Mercurie,</hi> carrying the similitude of <hi>Mercuries</hi> rodde, whereabout are two Serpents twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted. ☽ is the Character of the Moone, resembling the light part of the Moone in her prime. And by these considerations, may the Characters of the Planets be easily remembred.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(e)</hi> ♈ Is the Character of the <hi>Ramme,</hi> because in figure it resembleth a Rammes hornes. ♉ of the <hi>Bull,</hi> because it hath a resemblance of a Buls head. ♊ Of the <hi>Tvvinne,</hi> for the mutuall imbracements of them both. ♋ Of the <hi>Crabbe,</hi> because in figure it representeth the cleyes of a Crabbe: or (as <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Agrippa</hi> sayth, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Occult. Philos. Cap.</hi> 52▪) because it turneth both wayes, forward and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, in signification of the Sunnes progresse and regresse too and from this Signe. ♌ Of the <hi>Lion,</hi> for the length and wauing of his tayle. ♍ Of the <hi>Virgin,</hi> for the stalke and eare of Corne, which she is fayned to hold in her hand. ♎ Of the <hi>Ballance,</hi> because it beareth the figure of the crosse-beame of the Ballance. ♏ Of the <hi>Scorpion,</hi> for the wrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinges of his tayle. ♐ Of the <hi>Archer,</hi> because it hath the likenes of an Arrow. ♑ Of the <hi>Goate,</hi> for the turninges of his tayle. ♒ Of the <hi>VVater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> for the similitude of running Water. ♓ Of the
<pb facs="tcp:5076:26"/>
                     <hi>Fishes,</hi> because it figureth two Fishes linkt togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And by these considerations may the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of the Signes be kept in memorie.</p>
                  <p>There are besides these, innumerable Characters of Astronomie; as, the Characters of the Aspectes, the Characters of the 4. Triplicities, the Characters of 120. seuerall Coniunctions of the Planets, the Characters of diuers Constellations, the Characters the Olympicall letters, and Olympicall Spirites, (as they are tearmed) which I haue thought good not to trouble this Booke withall, there being no ordinarie or common vse of them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(f)</hi> § Signifieth a Paragraph; that is, (as <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianus Cossias</hi> defineth it) <hi>Quicquid sub vndsententia clauditur.</hi> Whatsoeuer is included in one sentence.</p>
                  <p>ff. Signifieth the Booke of Digestes; because the Graecians noted the volume of the Law called <hi>Pandectae,</hi> by the Greeke letter <hi>Pi,</hi> with a Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flex accent ouer it thus π̂ which in continuance of time▪ easily degenerated into the Character ff. By which Note, they signifie the Booke of Digestes; being a chiefe part of the <hi>Pandecte. Alciatus.</hi> All other Notes and Breuiatures, vsed in the Ciuill and Canon Law I omit, as being vnknowne to the most sort of people. As likewise for the same rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, I haue pretermitted the Characters vsed by the Physitians in their prescriptes: the Characters of Geometrie, Musicke, Magicke. Alchymie; they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing such as are familiar to none, but the Children of those Artes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:26"/>
               <head>Of Characters Heterogeneall. Chapt. 17.</head>
               <p>ANd so much concerning Homoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall notes of Wordes: it resteth to speake of Heterogenealles.</p>
               <p>An Heterogeneall, is a Note of a word expressed in a mixt kind of writing: as,
<list>
                     <item>1. Particles ioyned with
<list>
                           <item>Letters, as: <hi>Ouercome, Euery.</hi>
                              <gap reason="symbol" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>〈☐☐〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </item>
                           <item>Illiterals, as: <hi>Money, Fishmongor.</hi> ☽ ♓ ☽</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Letters ioyned with
<list>
                           <item>Particles, as: <hi>forefather, reuerse</hi>
                              <gap reason="symbol" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>〈☐☐〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </item>
                           <item>Illite. as: <hi>lion-kind, belfather. (a)</hi>
                              <gap reason="symbol" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>〈☐☐〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. Illiterals ioyned with
<list>
                           <item>Particles, as: <hi>Reason, Camphire.</hi>
                              <gap reason="symbol" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>〈☐☐〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </item>
                           <item>Letters: <hi>fatherhood, friendship.</hi>
                              <gap reason="symbol" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>〈☐☐〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Vnto these may be added as Heteroge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neals, <hi>(b)</hi> such words as are written in part or in whole, by the Character or Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of an other word or Syllable: Of which kind of words, this is the Rule. <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All Notes of a word, or part of a word, sauing Defectiues beginning with a Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well and regularly affixed, <hi>(c)</hi> may be vsed in composition, <hi>(d)</hi> to signifie a word or part of a word, harder noted <hi>(e)</hi> of like or neere sound: as, followeth.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5076:27"/>
                  <item>1 Literals Integrall, as: <hi>thereof, povverfull.</hi>
                     <gap reason="symbol" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>〈☐☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 Vnaffixed Particles, as: <hi>furlong despise.</hi>
                     <gap reason="symbol" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>〈☐☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 Aphthōg disiūcts <hi>Earnestnes, countermaūd</hi>
                     <gap reason="symbol" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>〈☐☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 Ordinarie Letters, as: <hi>Iecunde, condition</hi>
                     <gap reason="symbol" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>〈☐☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 Illiteralles, as: <hi>Commission, youngling</hi>
                     <gap reason="symbol" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>〈☐☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the .17. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> And of this sort are those vsuall Abreuiations of the names of Moneths, 7ber, 8ber, 9ber: for, Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember, October, Nouember.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> So called, because these are also of an other kind, different from the former.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(c)</hi> For Defectiues beginning with a Vowell, and regularly affixed, when they are vsed in composition, do not signifie their proper defectiue word, but that syllable onely which they note: as, <gap reason="symbol" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>〈☐☐☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, where the middle Particle signifieth <hi>An,</hi> the syllable which it noteth; and not <hi>Ansvver,</hi> the defectiue word, which without composition it should signifie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(d)</hi> That is, ioyned togither collaterally with some other note or notes, for the expressing of a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger word.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(e)</hi> Harder noted, that is, whose proper Note or Character is harder or more troublesome to be made: as, the proper Character of <hi>thereof,</hi> being <gap reason="symbol" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>〈☐☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> is harder to be made then <hi>theirof,</hi> a word of sound not vnlike to it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of the first Booke.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:5076:27"/>
            <head>THE SECOND BOOKE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Of part of a Word omitted. Chap. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Itherto touching the first part of <hi>Stenographie,</hi> consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting in the abreuiation of a Word: I come now to the second; which concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the abreuiation of a Sentence.</p>
               <p>The Abreuiation of a Sentence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth in two thinges: the abreuiation of part of a Sentence, and the abreuiation of a whole Sentence.</p>
               <p>The partes of a Sentence, are Worde, and Clause. <hi>(a)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A word in a Sentence <hi>(b)</hi> is abreuiated, either by Omission of some part thereof, or Contraction of the whole.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:28"/>
               <p>Part of a Word is to be omitted, when it may be vnderstood what it is by the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the speech.</p>
               <p>The part of a word so omitted, is either in the beginning, or in the ende thereof.</p>
               <p>In the beginning of a Word. First, H. W. and Y. <hi>(c)</hi> when their sound is drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the word before going: as,</p>
               <p>H. True friendship is onely amongst ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest men.</p>
               <p>W. It is ill to wish for death, but worse to feare it.</p>
               <p>Y. This yeere is the last yeeres Scholler, and the next yeeres Maister.</p>
               <p>Secondly, a Consonant of a word of no more then 2. syllables, after a word ending with a Consonant of the same sound: as,
<q>
                     <l>Mercie is with thee, that thou mayst be feared.</l>
                     <l>That which thou art about to do, forbeare to speake.</l>
                     <l>Oft haue I good done, thereof heare I neuer:</l>
                     <l>Once haue I ill done, thereof heare I euer.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>In the ende of a Word: to wit.</p>
               <p>First personall Terminations, <hi>(d)</hi> as;
<q>
                     <l>Pouertie compelleth a Sluggard to worke, and</l>
                     <l>Despaire enforceth a Coward to fight.</l>
                     <l>Warre makes Theeues, and Peace hanges them vp.</l>
                     <l>The more thou vnderstandest, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> more thou doubtest</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Literall or Syllabicall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections: <hi>(e)</hi> as,
<q>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5076:28"/>
                     <l>It is an honour to suffer rebuke for well doing.</l>
                     <l>That is not thine owne, which fortune can take away</l>
                     <l>And thou Melpomene helpen to indite, <hi>Chau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>These woefull lines that weepen as I write. <hi>Chau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, in Rythme; the ende of a line answering in sound the end of some other line before going.</p>
               <p>Immediately: as,
<q>
                     <l>When Fayth fayles in Priestes sawes,</l>
                     <l>And Lordes hestes are holden for lawes:</l>
                     <l>And Robberie is holden purchase,</l>
                     <l>And Lecherie is holden solace:</l>
                     <l>Then shall the lond of <hi>Albioun,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Be brought to great confusioun. <hi>Chaucer.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Mediately: as,
<q>
                     <l>Yf thou loose much, and gaine nought,</l>
                     <l>Yf thou spendest much, and mindest nought,</l>
                     <l>Yf thou borrow much, and pay nought,</l>
                     <l>And lookest in thy pursse, and findest nought,</l>
                     <l>Thou mayst be sory in thine hart, but say nought</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, any Letter or Syllable which the sense may supply: as; Pardon many thinges to others, but nought to thy selfe.</p>
               <p>It is better to be reprooued by an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, then commended by a flatterer.</p>
               <p>He accuseth <hi>Neptune</hi> wrongfully, that hath suffred twice shipwracke.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:29"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>All the Examples of the first Chapter are thus written. (f)</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>7 <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>7 <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the first Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> A Word is part of a Clause, and therefore of a Sentence. For, <hi>Pars partis est pars totius. Euclid.</hi> So seeing a Particle is part of a Letter; a Letter part
<pb facs="tcp:5076:29"/> of a Syllable, a Syllable part of a Word, a Word part of a Clause, a Clause part of a Sentence; therefore it followeth, that a Particle is part of a Sentence writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> Although the abreuiation of a Word be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated of both in the first part of Stenographie, and in the second, yet the Rules of Methode are not violated thereby; because in the first part, a word is considered in it selfe alone, without relation to other wordes ioyned with it: But in the seconde parr, a word is considered, as it respecteth other wordes, wherwith it is ioyned in the same sentence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(c)</hi> Eor H.W. and Y. haue the nature of Aspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(d)</hi> Personall terminations, as: <hi>est, es, eth,</hi> neede not to be added, seeing the Person is alwayes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed with the Verbe, in the English tongue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(e)</hi> The Letter N. is often added to wordes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in a Vowell, before a word beginning with a Vowell: as, An honour, not, A honour. Thine owne; not, Thy owne: and is then to be omitted. Syllabicall adiections vsed in the Latine tongue, are by this Rule to be omitted: as in, <hi>Adesdum, Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam (dum &amp; nam.)</hi> So in the Greeke, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctions called <hi>Parapleromaticall,</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(f)</hi> The first line conteyneth the examples of the first Rule: the second, the examples of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: the third, the example of the third Rule. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:30"/>
               <head>Of Wordes expressed by Metaphthonge Disiunctes. Chapt. 2.</head>
               <p>A Word is abreuiated by contractiō, whē it is expressed either by a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunct, or by an easier noted Word of like sound.</p>
               <p>By a Disiunct, to wit; Metaphthonge, or Aphthonge.</p>
               <p>Of the Abreuiation by Metaphthonge, all Wordes are capable, beginning with a Vowell, or H, and not exceeding two Syllables: as, <hi>(a)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The more <hi>you</hi> may be bolde with your friend, the lesse <hi>you</hi> ought.</p>
               <p>He that asketh <hi>ought</hi> impossible, denieth <hi>his owne</hi> request.</p>
               <p>Flatterie maketh <hi>each</hi> man a lyer to him selfe.</p>
               <p>Good thinges neuer <hi>appeare</hi> in their full beautie, till they turne their backes, and are departing.</p>
               <p>The spirit of God giueth <hi>vtterance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Griefe doth then decrease, when it is <hi>able</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5076:30"/> to increase no more.</p>
               <p>Forgetfulnes is the best remedie of things past <hi>hope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nothing is to be accounted profitable, which is not <hi>honest.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heere note, that if more wordes begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a vowel, or H, do come after one another, according to the order of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabet, in respect of their Vowels, they may all of them be referred as Disiunctes, to the same great Character: as, <hi>(b)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wo to them that <hi>are at ease in</hi> Sion.</p>
               <p>He is <hi>an yll Husband of his honour,</hi> that entreth into any action, the falling where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in may disgrace him more, then the cary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it through, can honour him.</p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the 2. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> The examples of this Chapter, and the two next, are diligently to be marked; because each of them illustrateth their Rule by a seuerall kinde of Disiunct: where note, that the wordes printed in smaller Letters, are those of which the Rule is giuen, and are to be expressed by Disiunctes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:31"/>
               <head>Of wordes expressed by Aphthonge disiunct. Chap. 3.</head>
               <p>OF the abreuiation by Aphthonge Disiunct: those words are capable which conteine one or more of those Syllables, which beginne or ende wordes of the seconde sort of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiues, as in these Examples:</p>
               <p n="1">1 Trueth <hi>by</hi> much wrangling is scattered <hi>to</hi> nothing. 2 One vnthankful man makes <hi>many</hi> fare the worse. 3 Euery fault ariseth in accompt greater or <hi>lesse, as the</hi> party is in degree, higher or lower that cōmitteth it. 4 In the kingdome of God, is the <hi>fullnesse</hi> of al ioy. 5 The weaker faction is firmer <hi>in</hi> Coniunction. 6 Beastes that are weake <hi>in the</hi> course, are nimble <hi>in the</hi> turne. 7 The Parentes indulgence, causeth the childes <hi>vntowardnesse.</hi> 8 The more excellent a thing is in his owne nature, the more vile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>becommeth, being</hi> abused.</p>
               <p>Note that if one of the regular Aph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonge wordes <hi>(a)</hi> do begin a line, it is to
<pb facs="tcp:5076:31"/> be noted, as if it belonged as finall Sylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to an other word before going: as, <hi>The</hi> Minde must beget godly wordes, and the Lippes bring them foorth. <hi>To</hi> receaue a benefite, is to sell libertie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>(a)</hi> That is, Wordes expressed by regular Aph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonges. 1. Booke. Chapt. 13.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Wordes of like sound. Chapt. 4.</head>
               <p>A Word is abreuiated, when it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed by an easier noted Word of like sound: as in these examples.</p>
               <p>An Enemie that hurtes me not, is <hi>as</hi> good <hi>as</hi> a Friend that doth me no good.</p>
               <p>A Spendthrift shall in the ende <hi>be</hi> a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, a Thiefe, or a Begger.</p>
               <p>That is kept with great perill, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie <hi>like.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Euerie argument <hi>against</hi> which nothing is sayd, is easily wonne.</p>
               <p>Neezing purgeth the Brayne, and cough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Lunges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They know</hi> not how to speake, that know
<pb facs="tcp:5076:32"/> not when to <hi>hold</hi> their peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There</hi> is no time good to one, which is not bad for an other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Clausiue Notes. Chapt. 5.</head>
               <p>NExt the abreuiation of a Word, commeth to be handled the abre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lause.</p>
               <p>A Clause is a part of a Sentence pronounced togi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her without pause, and distinguished from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rest by some clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siue Note.</p>
               <p>Clausiue notes vsed in this Art <hi>(a)</hi> are Notes either of distinction, or of reference.</p>
               <p>Distinctiue notes are foure: to wit,
<list>
                     <item>, Comma.</item>
                     <item>: Colon.</item>
                     <item>. Period.</item>
                     <item>? Interrogatiue.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>A Distinctiue Note when neede requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, <hi>(b)</hi> is to be placed vnder the last word of the clause, and at the right side thereof, as: <hi>Archelaus</hi> the Philosopher being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, Who was most in trouble? An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered; He that most desireth to be at rest.</p>
               <p>A note of Reference, is that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth
<pb facs="tcp:5076:32"/> a sentence or part thereof omitted or misplaced, into his proper place: And of these there are two sortes; the one sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, the other dubble.</p>
               <p>The Single note of Reference is thus marked (<gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>) and it is called commonly, The note of Interlineation, whose vse is to direct vs to that which is written aboue <hi>(e)</hi> the line, or in the margine.</p>
               <p>Aboue the line, as:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>That woman which would rather go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne a foolish Husband, then obay one that is wise and discreete, doth as if she de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired rather to lead ⁁<seg rend="above"> ⁁ a blind man in the vvay she knovves not,</seg> then to follow one that is skilfull in the way.</p>
               </q>
               <p>In the Margine, as:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Some in their Discourse, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire rather cōmendation of wit, in being able to holde all argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then of iudgement in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning what is true.<note n="⁁" place="margin"> As if it were a prayse to knowe what might be said, and not what should be thought.</note> Some haue certaine Common-places and Theames, wherein they are good, and want varietie: which kind of pouertie is for the most part tedious, &amp; now and then rediculous. <bibl>
                        <hi>F. Bacon</hi> in his <hi>Essayes.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:33"/>
               <p>A double Note of reference is thus mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked [ ], whereof the first is to be made at the beginning of a Clause, Sentence, or Speech; before which being alreadie writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>(f)</hi> some other sentence or speech should be placed: The last, is to be made at the ende thereof. And this double note signifieth all that Clause, Sentence, or Speech, that is included betweene them, to be read after the Sentence or speech next following, in that place where the sayd two Notes are placed togither, as:</p>
               <p>When the Citizens of <hi>Papia</hi> in <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> were at dissention, by reason of the faction betweene the <hi>Guelphes</hi> and the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>helines:</hi> The <hi>Gibelines</hi> procured a Fauoure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of theirs, called <hi>Facinus Canis,</hi> to come and assist them with a power of men, [where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of when the <hi>Gibelines</hi> did complaine vnto him, saying: that their goodes too were spoyled against agreement: He answered, that themselues were <hi>Gibelines,</hi> and should be safe; but their goodes were <hi>Guelphes,</hi> and must pay for it,] vpon agreement and couenant, that he should haue the goodes of the <hi>Guelphes</hi> for his pay. But he being once come into the Citie with his men of
<pb facs="tcp:5076:33"/> Warre, spared neither of them; his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers must be serued. [] The <hi>Gibelines</hi> of <hi>Papia</hi> could not foresee this; our Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes by them may. Let them leaue their brainsicke desires &amp; diuelish purposes, of bringing a <hi>Facinus Canis</hi> into their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; least by experience they feele (which God forbid) that though themselues be Catholickes, their Goodes may be Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques; perhaps some hereticall bloud in their bodyes also, by contagion of ours. <hi>D. Reignolds.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the 5. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> There are many Clausiue Notes besides which this Art respecteth not; as, ! the Note of Admiration. () Parenthesis. * An Asteriske, whereby <hi>Plato</hi> was wont to note certaine sentences as vnperfect. ℈ An Antigraph, wherby in auncient time, they noted a diuers sence in translation. ← A Dart, whereby they noted lyes, superflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous sentences, and wordes foysted into the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> A Dart with an Asteriske; which Note <hi>Aristarchus</hi> set vpon those Verses of <hi>Homer,</hi> that were not placed in their right order. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> For these Distinctiue notes in this Art, are very sparingly to be vsed, Except either the sence without them would be ambiguous, as in this example:
<q>
                        <pb facs="tcp:5076:34"/>
                        <l>Women are vertuous good and kinde.</l>
                        <l>What man can say that? they offende:</l>
                        <l>They serue their husbands with glad minde</l>
                        <l>Neuer, they deceiue them till their ende.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>In which example, if the Poyntes were made only at the ende of each line, the sence were much altered.</p>
                  <p>Or else, that the speech consisteth of very short sentences; as in these two Latine verses, describing the Simonie of some Clergie men.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Intus quis? tu quis? ego sum. quid quaeris? vt intrem.</l>
                     <l>Fers aliquid? non, sta foras. en fero. quid? satis. Intra.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(d)</hi> The vse of the Notes of Distinction is so commonly knowne, that it needeth not heere to declare it, but to note them onely.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(e)</hi> Aboue the line, rather then betweene the lines, because the clause referred, is not alwayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the lines, but sometime placed aboue the highest line: as,</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>A wise demaunder makes a man to consider ⁁<seg rend="above">
                           <hi>many thinges</hi>
                        </seg> and to know many other, which without hauing beene demaunded, he should neuer haue knowne. <bibl>
                           <hi>Machiauell.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(f)</hi> So that the vse of the dubble Clausiue note is this: If we haue written a Sentence, before which vpon better consideration an other Sentence should be written; and that there is not space enough to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terline it, or to write it in the Margine: Heere if we should blot out the former Sentence, it would require some time to write it againe: but by these Clausiue notes being included, it may stand still, and be read in his due place.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:34"/>
               <head>Of Clauses abreuiated by Omission. Chapt. 6.</head>
               <p>A Clause is abreuiated either by O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, or Contraction.</p>
               <p>By Omission, when some part thereof is left out. And this part of the clause is either neglected, or vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood.</p>
               <p>The part of a Clause neglected, are Wordes added without waight of matter, as: <hi>Ʋocémque his auribus hausi. Aeneid. 4.</hi> And I heard it with these eares. <hi>(a)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The part of a Clause omitted vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood, is vnderstood either by the order of writing, or by some note added beneath the lower line.</p>
               <p>By the order of Writing, either in Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, or common phrases.</p>
               <p>The order in Quotations is diuers, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Authour, whose authoritie is cited, <hi>(b)</hi> as:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1. Cor. 10.31.</hi> that is: The first Epistle of Paule to the Corinthians, the tenth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb facs="tcp:5076:35"/> and one and thirtieth verse.</p>
               <p>Common Phrases, <hi>(c)</hi> that is to say, such as we haue often occasion to vse, are to be expressed by the first letters of 2. 3. or 4. of the first wordes ioyned close togither: as. <hi>tco;</hi> that is, the coherence which these wordes haue with the former is after this maner. <hi>nlv.</hi> Now let vs make vse vnto our selues of that which hath been deliuered. And such like Phrases infinite.</p>
               <p>The part of a Clause omitted, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood by some note added beneath the lower line, is one or more Wordes repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the same sentence.</p>
               <p>If one Word onely be Immediately <hi>(d)</hi> repeated, it is vnderstood by this note <hi>(l)</hi> added to the worde repeated in the place of Distinction. Single, if it be repeated but once: Double, if it be repeated twice.</p>
               <p>Repeated but once, as: He that may do what he <hi>will, will</hi> do more then he may.</p>
               <p>Repeated twice, as: Ezech. <hi>21.27. Ouerthrowne, ouerthrowne, ouerthrowne,</hi> will I put it.</p>
               <p>If more Wordes be repeated, they are vnderstood by a straight line drawne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:35"/>
               <p>But the Repetition of more wordes, is either Immediate, or Mediate.</p>
               <p>If it be Immediate, it is repeated once or twise.</p>
               <p>If it be repeated but once, it is suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently vnderstood by the Line onely: as, <hi>Cant. 1.15. My Loue, behold thou art faire, behold thou art faire,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be repeated twise, the line must turne vp a little at the end of the last word: as, <hi>Ier. 7.4. Trust not in lying vanities saying: Heere is the Temple of the Lord, heere is the Temple of the Lord. heere is the Temple of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the repetition be mediate, then must a short line also <hi>(e)</hi> be drawne vnder the Word, last before going, in the place of Distinction, shewing that the wordes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnderlined, are there againe to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, as:
<q>
                     <l>The Tale that I told you, <hi>is as I tolde you.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And,</hi> the tale that I tolde you, <hi>is this:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If</hi> the tale that I told you, <hi>be not as I told you</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then vntold be</hi> the tale that I tolde you:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For,</hi> the tale that I told you, <hi>I told it amisse.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5076:36"/>
                  <head>Notes vpon the .6. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> In which Example, these Wordes, <hi>vvith these eares,</hi> may well be spared; because no man heareth without his eares. But of this Rule, and some other following in this Booke (as the Reader may easily obserue) we haue vse onely when we would write the generall sence of a speech deliuered, and not <hi>verbatim</hi> euery word thereof: Wherein, if the spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker from whose mouth we note, be very swift of deliuerie, so that he transporteth our imagination beyonde the indeuour of our handes; it shall not be amisse to write only the Verbes &amp; Substantiues, and other Wordes essentiall to the speech deliuered, reseruing a space for the rest which are of lighter circumstance, to be supplyed with Penne immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly after the speech is ended.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> For the Arithmeticall Figures, sometime note the Booke, sometime the Chapter, the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion, Centurie, Exercitation, Aphorisme, Leafe, Page, Colume, Section, Verse, Line. &amp;c. of any worke, according as it is distinguished by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(c)</hi> Euery man according to the subiect of his Writing vseth seuerall Phrases: it sufficeth therfore to giue instance by those two former Examples, how Phrases may be abridged.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(d)</hi> For Mediate repetitions of one Worde, are not to be respected: as; In this Example. <hi>(He that in time refuseth time, vvhen time vvell offered is: an other time shall seeke for time, but then of time shall misse.)</hi> The Word <hi>Time,</hi> is fully to be expressed by
<pb facs="tcp:5076:36"/> his proper Character, in all the places where it is vsed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(e)</hi> Besides that which was before drawne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sentence repeated.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Clauses abreuiated by Contraction. Chapt. 7.</head>
               <p>A Clause, is abreuiated by Contraction:</p>
               <p>First, of the sence of more Wordes into one, as: for, <hi>The great triangled Iland in the West,</hi> write <hi>England.</hi> For, <hi>The forerunner of our Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> write <hi>John.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, of more Wordes into one Character, as:
<list>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>The Iudgement hal. (a)</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>☊ <hi>The Dragons head. (b)</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>☋ <hi>The Dragons tayle.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>The chiefe poynt. (c)</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Frō the coronatiō of. (d)</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Hand ouer head. (e)</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>Preserued aliue (f)</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>θ <hi>Slaine in battaile.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>the Roman Empire (g)</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>And so foorth.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>·I· <hi>That is to say.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>It is.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the .7. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> This Character bearing the proportion of the snoute of a Shippe, may signifie the Iudgement
<pb facs="tcp:5076:37"/> Hall, because <hi>Moenius</hi> Consull of Rome, hauing ouercome the auncient Latines in a Sea skirmish, did set vp the Brasen snoutes of the enemies Shippes in the Iudgement Hall for a monument of his victorie: Which from thence forward vpon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion, was called <hi>Rostra,</hi> which in former times was called <hi>Forum. Liuius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> ☊ and ☋ are Astronomicall Figures, vsed to signifie the two Intersections called the <hi>Dragons Head,</hi> and the <hi>Dragons Tayle;</hi> because the deferent Circle cutting the Equant, maketh two Figures like these. <hi>Joan. de Sacrob.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(c)</hi> The reason of this Character, dependeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Armorie: For in Armorie there are 9. poyntes, contained in 3. Escocheons; which for speede in wryting, I reduce vnto a square forme, and place a Tittle in that poynt of that Escocheon, whose name I would signifie, as:
<q>The chiefe poynt in Hauking, is to hold fast.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>So likewise in the rest.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(d)</hi> This is in Armorie called <hi>A mund enuironed,</hi> and, <hi>a crosse Botone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> And it may be vsed in computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to signifie <hi>Frō the Conquest of a King, or Queene:</hi> because it hath been an auncient custome at the Coronation of the Kings of England, to giue them in the left hand a Scepter, and in their right hand a Globe with a Crosse standing vpright vpon it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(e)</hi> The reason of this signification is, because <hi>Iod</hi> the Hebrew letter signifying the hand, is placed ouer <hi>Resh</hi> an other Hebrew letter, signifying the Head.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(f)</hi> Of olde times, the Captaines after a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile fought, calling the Souldiers togither by name,
<pb facs="tcp:5076:37"/> noted those which were slaine in Battaile by the Greeke letter θ and those which were preserued aliue, by the Greeke letter <hi>Tau:</hi> whence sprung that Verse; <hi>O multum ante alias infoelix littera Theta.</hi> Also, <hi>Ezech</hi> 9.4. The Lord commaunded them to be marked with <hi>Tau</hi> in their forehead, whom he determined to preserue in the day of destruction.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(g)</hi> This Character, bearing the similitude of a Spread Eagle, may signifie the Romaine Empire, being the Ensigne thereof. The two heades of the Eagle seeme to note the partition of that one Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire into two: the Empire of the East, and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of the West.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Clauses neglected. Chapt. 8.</head>
               <p>HItherto concerning the Abreuiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the partes of a Sentence: It resteth to shew the Abreuiation of a whole sentence.</p>
               <p>A Sentence is abreuiated either by omission of some clause or clauses thereof, or by contraction of the whole.</p>
               <p>Clauses omitted, are either neglected, or vnderstood.</p>
               <p>Clauses are to be neglected, which are
<pb facs="tcp:5076:38"/> added without waight: as,</p>
               <p>First, Idle repetitions, as: <hi>Peter</hi> Went out and Wept bitterly: He Went out of the High priestes hall, he withdrew him selfe from all company, he remayned no longer among <hi>Cayaphas</hi> seruantes, but se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questred himselfe from their societie, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooke their fellowship, left their company, got him gone from among them, stayde no longer there, but went apart by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Needlesse Clauses, as: The Ambassadours not obteining peace, turnd backe againe to their house, from whence they went. <hi>(a)</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the .8. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> These Words <hi>(From vvhence they vvent)</hi> are needlesse to be added, being vnderstood by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Wordes <hi>(turnde backe againe to their house,) Legati non impetrata pace, retro domum, vnde abierant, abierunt. Cic.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:38"/>
               <head>Of Clauses vnderstood. Chapt. 9.</head>
               <p>CLauses Omitted, are vnderstood either when they are repeated in the same speech, or else when being the latter part of a Sentence, they are committed to memorie. when one, or more Clauses are repeated in the same speech, they followe the Rule of more wordes repeated: <hi>(a)</hi> as, in <hi>Psal. 137.</hi> this Clause <hi>(For his mercy endureth for euer)</hi> is repeated in euery verse: and to be signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied where it comes, by a short line.</p>
               <p>When being the later part of a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, they are committed to memorie, they are noted after the expressed part thereof, thus, &amp;. <hi>(b)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The latter part of a Sentence, is refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to memorie:</p>
               <p>First, when the Sentence is perfect in our mindes, as: <hi>In the beginning was the Word. &amp;. (c)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, when the later part of the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is a consequent of the former: as, In explicate Syllogismes, and Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
<pb facs="tcp:5076:39"/> fully distinguished by their partes.</p>
               <p>In explicate Syllogismes, <hi>(d)</hi> as: What soeuer is conteined in the World, is moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued continually by some kind of motion. But the Stones of the streete are conteined in the Worlde; therefore. &amp;c. <hi>(e)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In Comparisons fully distinguished by their partes, <hi>(f)</hi> as: It is a great danger to the Common-wealth, that any vicious person should be neere about the King, least he corrupt the Kings manners: which if he do, he deserueth more punishment, then if he peruert the good disposition of many priuate men. For, as he is more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be punished that poysoneth the Fountaine, then: that poysoneth many cuppes of water. &amp;. <hi>(g)</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the 9. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> Which Rule, is in the 6. Chapter of this Booke.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> &amp;c. Signifieth, <hi>And so foorth Chap</hi> 4. shewing that the later part of the Sentence is well knowne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(c) In the beginning vvas the VVord, and the VVord vvas vvith God, and that VVord vvas God. Iohn.</hi> 1.1. A Sentence so famous, as that it sufficeth to write onely the first clause thereof, and referre the rest to memorie. <hi>Augu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tine</hi> writeth, that not onely the faythfull, but the <hi>Platonickes</hi> made such accompt of
<pb facs="tcp:5076:39"/> this saying, as that they affirmed it worthy to be written with letters of Gold.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(d)</hi> That is to say, such as consist of the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, Assumption, and Conclusion, orderly placed, and not abridged into Enthymemes, or the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted forme.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(e)</hi> Who knoweth not that the Conclusion heere must needes be thus? <hi>Therfore the Stones of the st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eete are mooued continually by some kinde of motion.</hi> The Proposition is an Axiome of Philosophie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(f)</hi> That is to say, such as are described by their Proposition and Reddition: which are the two partes of Comparison.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(g)</hi> The Reddition, is by the Discourse going before the Comparison knowne to be thus. So be that corrupteth the manners of the King, is more worthy to be punished, then if he corrupted the manners of many priuate men.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Contraction of a Sentence by Figure. Chap. 10.</head>
               <p>A Sentence is abreuiated by Contracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it wholly, when it is expressed either by some apt Figure agreeable vnto it; or by some shorter Sentence equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualent in signification.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:40"/>
               <p>By some apt Figure; as for example, this sentence: (Enter in at the straight gate: for wide is the gate, and broad is the way, that leadeth to destruction; and many there be which go in thereat: Because the gate is straight, and the way narrow, that leadeth vnto life, and few there be that finde it. <hi>Math. 7.13.14</hi>) may be expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by this Figure Y. <hi>(a)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So a perfect Transition, shewing both what went before, and what followeth <hi>(b)</hi> may be expressed thus. ☜☞ An vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Transition, shewing that onely which went before, may be noted thus: ☜ shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that onely which followeth, thus, ☞ Digression from the matter thus, ☟ Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression to the matter thus, ☝<hi>(c)</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the 10. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(d)</hi> This Character was inuented by <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> to represent the estate and condition of man in this world. The lower part of the Character noteth Infancie: in which age it doth not appeare to what course of life the Childe is inclinable. The vpper part of the Character stretching two wayes; towards the right hand, and towardes the left, representeth the two wayes; in one of which, euery man walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. The right side, which is narrower, shewing
<pb facs="tcp:5076:40"/> the way of lyfe and saluation. The left, which is the broader, shewing the way of death and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction. Wherevpon <hi>Persius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Et tibiquae Sam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>os deduxit littera ramos,</l>
                     <l>Surgentem dextro monstrauit limite callem.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> A Transition is a Sentence which as it were bindeth other Sentences togither. And it is either perfect or imperfect. Perfect, which sheweth both what went before, and what followeth: as Hauing declared vnto you the sence and meaning of the Apostle in these words: I will now proceede to the Doctrines which may thence be gathered for our instruction. All Transitions of this kinde, may be expressed by two Handes, the one poynting forward, and the other backwarde, in s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gne that they shew both that which goeth before, and that which doth follow; which what it is, the Tractate it selfe suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently declareth. Notwithstanding, if we distrust our owne memorie, we may write after that dubble Note, the termes of the Transition; as in the former Example. The termes are Sence, and Doctrines: which are thus to be expressed.</p>
                  <p>An Imperfect Transition is of two sortes. First, it sheweth onely, either that which went before; as: And thus much shal suffice to haue spoken con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the occasion of these words of the Prophet. Or that which followeth; as: Let vs now apply this Doctrine to our selues, and see how neerely it concerneth vs.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it noteth either Digression from the matter, as: And heere although it be not incident to my Text, yet it shall not be vnprofitable to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider by the way, &amp;c. Or Regression and turning
<pb facs="tcp:5076:41"/> againe vnto the matter, as: But now to returne where we left.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(c)</hi> Vnto this Rule of contracting Sentences in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to some apt Figure, belong Emblemes: of which, there are and may be innumerable.</p>
                  <p>An Embleme is so called <gap reason="foreign" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which signifieth <hi>to place betvveene,</hi> or <hi>among.</hi> For in auncient times, the builders of Princes Pallaces, Noble mens Houses, and other sumptuous Edifices, vsed for the beautifying of their worke, to set heere and there in conuenient places of the Walles, faire squared Stones, or Timber worke; wherein were curiously grauen certaine Images and deuises, signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying some profitable instruction, And these Stones, or carued Images placed among others for orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment sake, were called <hi>Emblemata</hi> Emblemes. Hence it commeth, that Verses wherein the meaning of such Pictures and deuises is shewed, are called by a <hi>Metonymic</hi> Emblemes: whereof it shall suffice to giue instance by one Example in certaine Verses, concerning a Globe, whose circumference is euery where a like distant from the Center: made by that worthy man <hi>Theodorus Beza,</hi> in maner as followeth.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>circle with a point in the center</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <q>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5076:41"/>
                     <l>Cernis vt haec mediū cingat teres vndique punctū</l>
                     <l>Linea, &amp; hinc spacio distet et inde pari.</l>
                     <l>Scilicet illa refert quod nos tegit vndi{que} coelum,</l>
                     <l>Tellurem hoc punctum quod tenet ima notat.</l>
                     <l>Cur igitur doleas? quor sum (dic quaeso) labores,</l>
                     <l>Tu, patria pepulit quem pietatis amor?</l>
                     <l>Caelum si versus tendis, quocunque recedes,</l>
                     <l>Hinc spatio coelum cernis &amp; inde pari.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>In English thus.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Thou seest the middle poynt engirt with that round line,</l>
                     <l>which hence and thence doth distaunce like maintaine:</l>
                     <l>That line doth note the heauen, which girdleth vs arounde,</l>
                     <l>that point pointes out the earth and thinges agrounde.</l>
                     <l>Then tell me thou? whom loue of pietie diuorc't</l>
                     <l>from thine owne home, what thee to griefe enforc't?</l>
                     <l>What meanes thy toyle? For if thy iourney be to Heauen,</l>
                     <l>from hence or thence thou seest the distance euen.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Translated by S. P.</p>
                  <p>And by the benefite of such Emblemes referred to a due place in our imagination, the memorie also is much holpen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>Of contraction of Sentences by Logicke. Chap. 11.</head>
               <p>A Sentence is expressed by some shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Sentence equiualent with it in sence, by the benefit of iudgement <hi>(a)</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5076:42"/> either Axiomaticall or Dianoëticall. <hi>(b)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Example of a Sentence contracted by Axiomaticall iudgment.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>At last the golden Orientall gate,</l>
                  <l>Of greatest H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>auen gan to open faire,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bus</hi> fresh as Bridegroome to his mate,</l>
                  <l>Came daunsing foorth shaking his deawie haire,</l>
                  <l>And hurles his glistring beames through gloomie aire</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>E. Spencer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Contracted thus: <hi>At last the Sunne arose.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By Dianoëticall iudgement, to wit, Syllogisticall or Methodicall.</p>
               <p>Example of a Sentence contracted by Syllogisticall iudgement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cic. 1. Tuscul.</hi> In the knowledge of the nature of Mans soule, we may not doubt, (vnlesse peraduenture we be dull and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den witted in naturall thinges) but that in the soule, there is nothing mixt, nothing compact, nothing conioyned or knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, nothing compounded, nothing double: Which being so, surely the soule may neither be seuered in it selfe, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, nor rent in peeces, nor pluckt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunder; and therefore not die: For death is nought else, but the parting, seperating, and plucking in sunder of those partes, which before death, were ioyned togither
<pb facs="tcp:5076:42"/> by some copulation.</p>
               <p>Contracted thus: <hi>All mortall thinges are compound; the soule is not compound:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not mortall.</p>
               <p>An Example of Sentences abreuiated by Methodicall iudgement, is heere deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered in a Recapitulation of this whole worke, <hi>(a)</hi> And that vnder two formes, in two Tables heerevnto adioyned, marked thus. ❀</p>
               <div type="notes_on_chapter">
                  <head>Notes vpon the .11. Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(a)</hi> Iudgement, is the second part of Logique; by the benefite whereof, a long Sentence may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily be contracted into a shorter. For that which the Rhetoritian deliuereth at large, the Logician com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priseth in a few wordes: In which respect, <hi>Zeno</hi> compared Rhetorique to the Hand open and stret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched foorth: Logique, to the Hand shut close, as if Rhetorique were nothing else but enlarged Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gique; and Logique nothing else but contracted Rhetorique: Whereas this difference consisteth not in the Artes, but in the Artificers themselues.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(b)</hi> Axioma is taken for an Enunciation or Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, pronouncing any thing to be, or not to be. And therefore the iudgement arysing from such Enunciations, is called Axiomaticall. Dianoia, sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth the discourse of the minde, whereby one Axiome is drawne out of another. And therefore the iudgement arising from such discourse of minde, is called Dianoëticall.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5076:43"/>
                  <p>¶ Although the Art of Stenographie hath heere been handled, chiefly as it concerneth the English tongue; and examples giuen thereof onely: Yet any Word or Sentence of what other Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage soeuer, maybe fully written thereby, as: <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> Which is the abreuiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by Stenographie, of these two Greeke Verses. <bibl>
                        <hi>Iliad.</hi> 9.</bibl>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Latiné sic reddidit Nicolaus Borbonius.</l>
                        <l>Non minus odi illum quam nigri limen Auerni,</l>
                        <l>Cuius mens aliud sentit, quam lingua loquatur.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
                  <p>In English thus.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>I hate him as I hate Hell gates,</l>
                     <l>That one thing thinkes, another prates.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:5076:43"/>
            <head>A Direction for STEGANOGRAPHIE; or, Secret Writing.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing finished the Arte of <hi>Stenographie,</hi> or, <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Writing,</hi> heere are added a few lines con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Steganographie,</hi> or <hi>Secret Writing:</hi> not with purpose to handle it fully in the seuerall partes and kindes thereof, but onely in sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of what was promised in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this Booke, to giue a few Rules for the same; yet such, as being practised togither with those before deliuered, will enhable the Reader vnder one labour, to write both secretly, and compendiously.</p>
            <p>The first Rule is, that the signification of Particles be altered, to note by them other Letters: that whereas before in this
<pb facs="tcp:5076:44"/> Booke <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
               </gap> standeth alwayes for <hi>a.</hi>
               <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
               </gap> for <hi>b.</hi>
               <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
               </gap> for <hi>c.</hi> &amp;c. We may vse <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
               </gap> to signifie <hi>b.</hi>
               <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
               </gap> to signifie <hi>c.</hi>
               <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
               </gap> to signifie <hi>d.</hi> and so likewise changing the power of the rest of the Letters. Which kind of Obscure writing <hi>Augustus</hi> in a Letter to his Sonne, willed should be vsed betweene them; that when they wrote their mindes each to other, they should expresse euery letter which they had occasion to write, by the Character of the letter following next in the order of the Alphabet, and for z. which is the last letter to double <hi>A.</hi> As, if this sentence, <hi>(Religion is the meane be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Athesme and Superstition,)</hi> should be written according to <hi>Augustus</hi> his directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it were thus to be expressed. <hi>Sfmkhkpo kt uif nfbof cfuxff of buifktnf boe twqfstukukpo.</hi> After this maner may be altered the signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of euery Particle, or of as many, or as few of them, as is thought good, which will be nothing hard at the first en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the practise of this Arte, being then as easie to expresse each Letter by an other Particle, as by that which is appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate to it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the places of small Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters
<pb facs="tcp:5076:44"/> about the great, are to be changed, as by making the place of <hi>A.</hi> to be where regularly, the seate of <hi>E</hi> is. And the place of <hi>E</hi> where regularly the seate of <hi>I</hi> is: and so foorth of the rest. As if this saying of <hi>Thucydides (She is the best Woman, of whose prayse or disprayse is least spoken)</hi> should be written by vsing this, and the former Obseruation, it were thus to be expressed, <gap reason="foreign" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Which Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters being read according to the Rules of Stenogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, bring foorth these strange and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne wordes: <hi>Taaïos kittaa xuneo pro xaäut qsetur eqset jtam, therfore.</hi> In like order may be disposed the small Characters, by changing the places of some, or all of thē.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it yeeldeth no smal furtherance to Secret Writing, if new Illiterall Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters be inuented and vsed for certaine words: betweene which words and their Characters, appeareth some Analogie and proportion of reason, at least, in the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of him that inuenteth them. Of which priuate Illiteralles, heere follow diuers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, which may giue light to the inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many other the like Characters.</p>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:45"/>
               <item>✚ <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Dunstaple.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Neptune.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>{anchor} <hi>Saleucus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Amyntas.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Geomantie</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>World.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>☾ <hi>Ockamie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Diademe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ʋictorie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>▵ <hi>Pyramides</hi>
               </item>
               <item>∵ <hi>Cluster.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>∷ <hi>Plague.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>.˙.˙ <hi>Pestilence.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fire.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Winde.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>quarterly.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Talentc.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Hurte.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Bullet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Wound.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>= <hi>Equality.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Entangle.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ecclipse.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Sphaere.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>shipwrack</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>appoynted</hi>
               </item>
               <item>⋮ <hi>Order.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Shipp.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Hood.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>⊕ <hi>Counter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>… <hi>Embroder</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Antesigne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>ה <hi>Behold.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>ד <hi>Hand.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>ל <hi>Spit.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>ב <hi>Infant.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>כ <hi>Crowne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>ר <hi>Head.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>ת <hi>Terme.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>As touching the relation which these wordes haue to their Characters, it stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>England</hi> is signified by a plaine Crosse, because the Christian Kinges of <hi>England</hi> boare a plaine red Crosse (commonly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>S. George his Crosse,</hi>) and <hi>Englishmen</hi> are yet distinguished in the fielde, and vpon the seas, from other Nations by the redde Crosse in their white Flagges &amp; Ensignes. So <hi>Arcadia</hi> may be signified by the <hi>Halfe Moone,</hi> because the people of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
<pb facs="tcp:5076:45"/> woare the <hi>Halfe Moone</hi> vpon their Shooes in memorie of their Antiquitie. For (as the Poets faine) when after <hi>Deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calions</hi> Floud, the <hi>Arcadians</hi> being newly spronge from Trees, about the change of the Moone, saw within three or foure dayes after the Moone appearing in her prime, they thought thēselues to be more auncient then the Moone; and therefore wore the <hi>Halfe Moone</hi> vpon heir Shooes. Wherevpon <hi>Ouid de Fast. lib.</hi> 2.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ante Jouem genitum, terras habuisse feruntur</l>
               <l>Arcades, &amp; Luna gens prior illa fuit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Though the cause of this fiction seemeth to be, for that the <hi>Arcadians</hi> first founde out the course of the Moone. So may we signifie <hi>Persia</hi> by the <hi>Bow,</hi> because the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sians</hi> had a <hi>Bow</hi> painted on their Shieldes. <hi>Fraunce</hi> by the <hi>Floure deluce: Ireland</hi> by the <hi>Harpe,</hi> and such like.</p>
            <p>The second Character bearing the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblance of a Staple and Ring, may sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the Towne of <hi>Dunstaple,</hi> called first <hi>Dunningestaple:</hi> which giueth in Armes the Staple and the Ring. And in like maner other Citties, Townes, Corporations, &amp;c. may be signified by that especiall thing
<pb facs="tcp:5076:46"/> which they giue in Armes, so that it be short and easie to be made.</p>
            <p>The third Character may be vsed for <hi>Neptune</hi> (whom the Poetes fayne to haue gouernement ouer the Seas) because he is supposed to carie a three-forked <hi>Mace</hi> or <hi>Scepter,</hi> in signe of the triple vse which Water hath; being profitable for Nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for Drinke, and for Washing. So <hi>Hercules</hi> may be signified by a <hi>Clubbe,</hi> which is supposed to be his weapon. <hi>Apollo</hi> by an <hi>Arrow. Pallas</hi> by a Speare, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The name of <hi>Seleucus</hi> may be noted by an <hi>Anchor,</hi> because when he was borne, the print of an Anchor was found vpon his thigh: for which cause, he and his suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessours wore the badge of an <hi>Anchor</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their thighes. So <hi>Vlisses</hi> may be signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by a <hi>Dolphin,</hi> because he boare it in Armes. <hi>Agamemnon</hi> by a <hi>Lion,</hi> &amp;c. And in like manner Noblemens names may be noted by somewhat in their Coates, Crestes Cognisance. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The fift Character is a <hi>Sheepebrand,</hi> or a <hi>Chapmans marke</hi> set vpon the wares which he buyeth, to marke them for his owne. And we may well signifie the names of
<pb facs="tcp:5076:46"/> such men as we know, by their Marke, or some note agreeable to their trade: which is an vsuall and common practize among Countrey Farmers that can not read, who with a Chaulke stone set downe their rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koninges with seuerall men, by such Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters as this.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
               </gap> Signifieth <hi>Geomantie,</hi> because that Art prescribeth Diuination by diuers rowes of Tittles, casually made by the Artificer in such order as these.</p>
            <p>The seauenth Character signifieth the <hi>Worlde,</hi> because all the Spheres of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, the Fire and the Aire, do encompasse the Globe of the Earth and Water; as the White doth the Yelke of an Egge: or, as in an Onion many coates do the middle part thereof.</p>
            <p>☾ Signifieth <hi>Ockamie,</hi> (which is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Metall betweene Tinne and Syluer; whereof Organe pipes, and Sergeantes Maces are made) because this Figure is like ☽, which signifieth <hi>Syluer,</hi> as <hi>Ockamie</hi> in shew is like Syluer.</p>
            <p>The ninth Character signifyeth a <hi>Diademe,</hi> because it is like the Linke of a Wreath. For a <hi>Diademe</hi> is a Wreath of
<pb facs="tcp:5076:47"/> Sylke or fine Linnen; such as the <hi>Souldan</hi> of <hi>Babilon,</hi> and other Princes wore about their heades. And it is called a <hi>Diademe, apo tou diadein,</hi> of Compassing about. This kinde of Attire for the Kinges head, may seeme after a sort deriued from Nature. For the King among the Bees hath a small white Circle like a Diademe about his head, and the rest of the Bees haue none. <hi>Plin. lib. 11. Cap. 16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The tenth Character, hauing the similitude of a Palme branch, signifyeth <hi>Victorie,</hi> because as the Palme tree although it haue great waightes layde vpon it, still mounteth vpward: So an heroicall spirit, giueth not place to Calamitie, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth in striuing against them which op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose him, till he hath gotten the victorie. <hi>Plutarch lib. 8. Symposiac.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pyramides</hi> were certaine solide Pillars in <hi>Aegipt</hi> of Stone and Bricke, built like Steeples, broade at the bottome, &amp; sharpe at the toppe; extended in height farre aboue all other Buildinges, wrought with mans hand: vnder which, the <hi>Aegiptian</hi> Kinges were intombed. Among which, there was one built at the cost of <hi>Rhodopis</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:5076:47"/> the Harlot; which was the most famous worke of the rest, and worthily reckoned among the seauen Wonders of the world, as well for the curious and stately worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manship thereof, as that she by the gaine of her whooredomes was able to builde a monument more sumptuous, then those of the Kinges.</p>
            <p>∵ Is the Character of the Hebrew Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well <hi>Segol,</hi> which signifieth a Cluster of Grapes: whereunto the Figure answereth in likenesse.</p>
            <p>∷ Signifieth the Plague, because it is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten seene, to arise in small spottes vpon the body of him that is vsited therewith. This Character, and some of them that follow, with many more, not heere inser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, were found in certaine olde Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, placed with diuers strange words, letters, and numbers: which among the simple people, are reputed to conteyne Prophecies and Predictions of great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to ensue. And some Impostors haue taken vpon them, by these to ominate and speake of many thinges to come, to the deluding and beguiling of the credulous: Whereas in deed they conteyne no such
<pb facs="tcp:5076:48"/> matter, as vpon some paynes taken there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I easily discouered.</p>
            <p>□ Signifieth Quarterly, because it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth an Escocheon parted quarterly, and reduced into a square forme. And in like maner may the other 8. Partitions be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: as, □ <hi>partie per pale,</hi> □ <hi>partie perfesse. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Rundle of the colour of Gold, is called by Herehaults <hi>A Beysant,</hi> which is in Englishe <hi>A Talente.</hi> And therefore I note a <hi>Talente</hi> by a Circle with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle in it for or, which signifieth it, to be of the colour of Gould. So likewise I note the word <hi>Hurte,</hi> by a Rundle, with in it for <hi>Azure blew. Bullet,</hi> by a Rundle with in it for <hi>Sables Blacke. Wounde,</hi> by a Circle, with in it for <hi>Purpure Purple:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause these rundles being of these colours, signifie these wordes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He,</hi> the Hebrew letter, signifieth <hi>Behold.</hi> The rest following, are also He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew letters, whose names haue that sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification in English, which is before pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with them. And all other Hebrew letters are significant, and may likewise be vsed, to signifie the wordes noted by their name.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5076:48"/>
            <p>Vnto these Illiterall Characters, the Hieroglyphicks also may be referred, which were certaine Pictures and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters inuented in auncient time by the Priestes of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> for their owne priuate vse, to expresse the mysteries of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by, that they might not be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood of the common sort. So by the Picture of an E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mot, they s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gnified labor and industrie, because the Emmot labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in Summer to prouide foode for her selfe in Winter. By the Picture of a <hi>Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin,</hi> Swiftnesse: because the <hi>Dolphin</hi> is sayd to be the swiftest in motion of all liuing creatures. By the Picture of a <hi>Serpent</hi> cast in a circle, and holding his tayle in his mouth, they noted the Yeere; because the Sunne, which measureth the Yeere by his circular motion, is as it were turned againe into his first station, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning each yeere the same course which it did the yeere before: wherevpon were made these Verses.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Serpens Annus ego sum, Sol sic circinat, in quo</l>
               <l>Qui fluxit pridē, status est nunc temporis idem.</l>
               <l>Io. de sacr.</l>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:5076:49"/>
            <p>And therefore the <hi>Paenicians</hi> in such a shape, worshipped <hi>Fanus</hi> as God of the Yeere. <hi>Macrobius.</hi> In like maner, they signified <hi>Fonde Loue</hi> by a <hi>She Ape imbrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of her young ones:</hi> for the Ape bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth foorth two, whereof she loueth the one, but hateth the other: That which she loueth, she huggeth to her selfe by such hard imbracementes, that she killeth it; and then hauing but one left, she nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risheth it with lesse fondnesse. So they represented <hi>A Deceiuer</hi> by a <hi>Cuttle Fish,</hi> which when the Fisherman is readie to catch her with his handes, casteth foorth a blacke slimie humour like Inke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the water being darkned, she conueieth her selfe away vnseene. So they noted <hi>Prouidence</hi> by a <hi>Beare</hi> going backwarde into her Caue, that her footinges being seene to be outward, the Hunter might imagine that she was gone abroad. And many such like Hieroglyphickes were in vse among the auncient <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> by which the secrets and mysteries of their Learning and Religion, were after a sort locked vp from the Vulgar people, and neuer applyed to common vses, but
<pb facs="tcp:5076:49"/> knowne onely to the Priestes, who had been taught the same in priuate from their Elders. <hi>Suydas.</hi> Them which desire a further insight into these <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, I referre to the writinges of <hi>Orus, Ʋalerianus, Pierius,</hi> and others that haue written therof at large.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is an helpe in Secret writing, to varie the Illiterall Characters into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers significations, which may be done by addition of some short Note to them in place conuenient: as for example. Plane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie Characters accompanied with a tittle, may signifie in the place of <hi>A,</hi> the planetarie day, in the place of <hi>E,</hi> the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netarie mettall, in the place of <hi>I</hi> the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Planetarie Members of mans body, in the place of <hi>O</hi> the Planetarie Colours, in the place of <hi>u</hi> the planetarie Age. Againe, the Planetarie Characters accompanied with a Comma in steed of a Tittle, may signifie in the first place, the planetarie Nature: in the second, a plane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie Stone: in the third, a planetarie Tree: in the fourth, a planetarie Beast: In the fift a Planetarie Foule, as:
<table>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5076:50"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell> . ♄ Saturne.</cell>
                     <cell> . ♃ Iupiter.</cell>
                     <cell> . ♂ Mars.</cell>
                     <cell> . ☉ Sunne.</cell>
                     <cell> . ♀ Venus.</cell>
                     <cell> . ☿ Mercurie.</cell>
                     <cell> . ☽ Moone.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> · ♄ Saturday.</cell>
                     <cell> · ♃ Thursday</cell>
                     <cell> · ♂ T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>usday.</cell>
                     <cell> · ☉ Sunday.</cell>
                     <cell> · ♀ Fryday.</cell>
                     <cell> · ☿ Wednisday.</cell>
                     <cell> · ☽ Munday.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <seg rend="sup">.</seg> ♄ Leade.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <seg rend="sup">.</seg> ♃ Tinne.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <seg rend="sup">.</seg> ♂ Iron.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <seg rend="sup">.</seg> ☉ Gold.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <seg rend="sup">.</seg> ♀ Copp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <seg rend="sup">.</seg> ☿ Quicksiluer</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <seg rend="sup">.</seg> ☽ Syluer.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>♄ <seg rend="sup">.</seg> the Milt.</cell>
                     <cell>♃ <seg rend="sup">.</seg> the Liuer</cell>
                     <cell>♂ <seg rend="sup">.</seg> Gall.</cell>
                     <cell>☉ <seg rend="sup">.</seg> Hart.</cell>
                     <cell>♀ <seg rend="sup">.</seg> Kidneys.</cell>
                     <cell>☿ <seg rend="sup">.</seg> Lightes.</cell>
                     <cell>☽ <seg rend="sup">.</seg> Brayne.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>♄ · Blacke.</cell>
                     <cell>♃ · Blew</cell>
                     <cell>♂ · Redde.</cell>
                     <cell>☉ · Yellow.</cell>
                     <cell>♀ · Greene.</cell>
                     <cell>☿ · Purple</cell>
                     <cell>☽ · White.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>♄ . Dotage.</cell>
                     <cell>♃ . Oldage.</cell>
                     <cell>♂ . Firmeage.</cell>
                     <cell>☉ . Middleage</cell>
                     <cell>♀ . Youth.</cell>
                     <cell>☿ . Childhood.</cell>
                     <cell>☽ . Infancie.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>, ♄ Melancholy</cell>
                     <cell>, ♃ Religion.</cell>
                     <cell>, ♂ Couragious</cell>
                     <cell>, ☉ Liberall.</cell>
                     <cell>, ♀ Pleasant.</cell>
                     <cell>, ☿ Wittie.</cell>
                     <cell>, ☽ Vncōstant</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>▪ ♄ Loadstone</cell>
                     <cell>▪ ♃ Sapphyre.</cell>
                     <cell>▪ ♂ Rubie.</cell>
                     <cell>▪ ☉ Topaze.</cell>
                     <cell>▪ ♀ Emerauld.</cell>
                     <cell>▪ ☿ Amathist.</cell>
                     <cell>▪ ☽ Chrystall.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>' ♄ Hebene.</cell>
                     <cell>' ♃ Oake.</cell>
                     <cell>' ♂ Fugh.</cell>
                     <cell>' ☉ Baytree.</cell>
                     <cell>' ♀ Myrtle.</cell>
                     <cell>' ☿ Orengetree.</cell>
                     <cell>' ☽ Vine.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>♄ ' Moule.</cell>
                     <cell>♃ ' Hart.</cell>
                     <cell>♂ ' Wolfe.</cell>
                     <cell>☉ ' Lion.</cell>
                     <cell>♀ ' Goate.</cell>
                     <cell>☿ ' Ape.</cell>
                     <cell>☽ ' Catte.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>♄ ▪ Lapwinge.</cell>
                     <cell>♃ ▪ Eagle.</cell>
                     <cell>♂ ▪ Vulture.</cell>
                     <cell>☉ ▪ Swanne.</cell>
                     <cell>♀ ▪ Doue.</cell>
                     <cell>☿ ▪ Storke.</cell>
                     <cell>☽ ▪ Owle.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>And in such sort, may any other Stones, Trees, Beastes, Foules, Fishes, Reptiles, Hearbes, &amp;c. be expressed by some other Note added to their Planetarie Character in the Metaphthonge places: which he that will doe, may finde plentifull Examples in <hi>Cornelius Agrip. de Occult. Phil.</hi> and in a Booke entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The Kalender of Scripture,</hi> in the ex-position of the name <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5076:50"/>
            <p>Heere although instance be giuen only in the Planetarie Characters how they may be varied in signification: yet the Characters of Number, of the .xij. Signes, and the rest, with infinite more that might be added, may with like shew of reason, haue other wordes referred vnto them. Yet with this caution, that no Particles be placed about the Character so varied.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, the poynctes of Distinction are to be expressed by vnaffixed Particles, by ordinarie Letters, or by Illiterall Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters (as seemeth best) placing not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding Distinctiue Notes vnder certaine great Characters, not ending the clause or sentence. For this will easily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile the search of the most curious, when he shall imagine the clause or sentence to ende where it doth not, and accompt them for significant notes of words, which are but dumbe notes of distinction.</p>
            <p>Beside these fiue Rules for Secret Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, there are diuers other Obseruations heere omitted, as depending vpon some former Rule. Such as are the referring of other words to the Defectiue Characters,
<pb facs="tcp:5076:51"/> the changing of the signification of Illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls, the contraction of ordinarie Phrases into two or three Letters, or of whole sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences into one Character: Which Rules and Obseruations he that vseth, may write any thing so secretly, as that it shall not be found out by an other what it is, by all those wittie and acute deuises, mentioned by <hi>Baptista Porta,</hi> for the triall of all such kindes of Writing, in his Booke <hi>De Furt. liter. Notis.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Ʋiue, Vale: si quid nouisti rectius ist is,</l>
               <l>Candidus imperti: si non, his vtere mecum.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="summary_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:5076:51"/>
            <list>
               <item>❀ <hi>Stenographie</hi> concerneth the Abreuiation of
<list>
                     <item>A Word. (First <hi>Booke</hi>)
<list>
                           <item>By Characters
<list>
                                 <item>Great. Chapt. 1.</item>
                                 <item>Small Chapt. 2.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>either
<list>
                                 <item>In the parts thereof
<list>
                                       <item>Letter, which abreuiated is called a Particle
<list>
                                             <item>Vnchangeable. Chapt. 3.</item>
                                             <item>Changeable. Chapt. 4,</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Syllable, abreuiated in reguard of the
<list>
                                             <item>Sound, by
<list>
                                                   <item>Omission, the part omitted being
<list>
                                                         <item>Neglected,
<list>
                                                               <item>Vowell. Chapt. 5.</item>
                                                               <item>Consonant. C. 6.</item>
                                                            </list>
                                                         </item>
                                                         <item>Vnderstood. Chapt. 7.</item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                   <item>Contraction. Chapt. 8.</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>The Characte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                                   <desc>•</desc>
                                                </gap> Chapt. 9.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Wholy by a note
<list>
                                       <item>Homogeneall
<list>
                                             <item>Literal.
<list>
                                                   <item>Integrall,
<list>
                                                         <item>Of one Syllable. Chap. 10.</item>
                                                         <item>Of more Syllables. Chap 11.</item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                   <item>Defectiue of the
<list>
                                                         <item>Eirst sort. Chapt. 12.</item>
                                                         <item>Second sort. Chapt. 13.</item>
                                                         <item>Third sort. Chapt. 14.</item>
                                                         <item>Fourth sort Chapt. 15.</item>
                                                      </list>
                                                   </item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>Illiterall Chapt. 16.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>Heterogeneall. Chapt. 17.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>A Sentence (2. <hi>Booke</hi>)
<list>
                           <item>In part
<list>
                                 <item>Word by
<list>
                                       <item>Omission C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>ap. 1.</item>
                                       <item>Contraction into a note. Chap. 5.
<list>
                                             <item>Disiunct
<list>
                                                   <item>Metaph. Cha. 2.</item>
                                                   <item>Aphthon. Cha. 3</item>
                                                </list>
                                             </item>
                                             <item>of another word. Cahpt. 4.</item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Clause. Cap. 5. by
<list>
                                       <item>Omission. Chap. 6.</item>
                                       <item>Contraction. Chap 7.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>Wholy by
<list>
                                 <item>Omitting some Clauses
<list>
                                       <item>Neglected. Chapt. 8.</item>
                                       <item>Vnsterstood. Chapt. 9.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Contracting it into
<list>
                                       <item>A shorter Sentence. Chapt. 10,</item>
                                       <item>An apt Figure. Chapt. 11.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:5076:52"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>phie co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cerne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>tion of a
<list>
                        <item>Word</item>
                        <item>Sentence</item>
                     </list>
                  </head>
                  <figDesc>tree-like diagram</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5076:52"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5076:53"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5076:53"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>